Yo Yehudi: Hello. So hi, I'm here
to talk to you very briefly
about open licenses. The slides
that I'm sharing are shared with
a creative commons by license,
developed by open life science
and then modified by me, I am
not a lawyer, I only play one
one playing board games. Okay,
so a little bit about me, I am
the reproducibility librarian at
the Health Science Center
libraries at the University of
Florida. My pronouns are he him
his and my Twitter handle is how
and why do you feel free to
reach out to me if you have
questions about research,
reproducibility or other related
topics. So the goal and talking
about licensing in the context
of open life science is an open
projects is we would like other
people to be able to use, remix,
and share our the work that
we're doing in our open
projects. And we achieve that by
making sure that we have in our
open projects, explicit
documentation about how other
people can use and remix and
share it. And so we're going to
go through these slides. And
hopefully, if there's time, you
know, have the ability to have
short discussion or answer any
quick questions about this, with
the goal being that you will
eventually know and understand
the importance, and how exactly
to do the task of adding an open
license to your work. Okay. And
so going back to kind of the
intent behind all of this, the
open leadership framework talks
about open leaders, as designing
and building projects that
empower others, right, we think
about, were doing these
projects, because usually,
because we care about doing work
that, you know, helps other
people, whether those are people
in our communities or outside
our communities. And so that's
kind of where we think about one
way in which, you know, we do
that interaction is by having
our work be shared in a way that
other people can, can use it.
And so this falls in this box of
the open leadership framework of
building for sharing and making
sure that we have explicitly in
the building of our project, a
way that we share the work.
Okay, so some some
misconceptions that I think I
want to address when talking
about licensing. Because it is a
it is a complex topic, and it
does relate to things like
copyright, and academic credit.
But licensing is not the same
thing. And so some brief kind of
points to make really quickly,
just because you share something
on the internet, or GitHub or
someone else share something on
the internet, or GitHub does not
automatically allow other people
to use it. If you are sharing
work with a license, it does not
by default, give away your
copyright. So you can share work
with a free license and an open
license like Creative Commons,
that does not prevent you from
publishing your work or selling
your work or in other ways
monetizing your work. And
finally, a work that has been
shared with an open license, you
can use it and other people can
use it, they don't have to cite
you necessarily. So it can be
legal to use the work without
citing you. But in an academic
setting, if you are doing an
academic research, that's still
considered a violation of
academic ethics. And that is
something that you would pursue
if it's a problem using academic
means. Because that can be
plagiarism. Okay, so some some
kind of common elements. When we
talk about licenses, there are
of course, many different ways
you can, you can give other
people permissions on so many
different example licenses. And
the kinds of things that we
think about in terms of
including in the open license
are how people can use your
work, how people can modify your
work, and how they can share
your work and redistribute
either the original or the
modified work to other people.
And so, yeah,
some of these elements also
include attribution. So a lot of
the open licenses that are in
use gela require that if the
work is being reshare by someone
else, that the job Original
authors are credited. So
examples of this are the
Creative Commons by license,
which has a this attribution
clause, and almost all the other
licenses that will be mentioned
today. And one exception to this
one important exception to this
is the Creative Commons zero
license, which effectively is
putting something into the
public domain and waiving your
copyright to, to whatever it is
that you are sharing using the
CC zero license. So some some
kind of advance advanced
complications within this topic
of open license. So I've put
these as I list these as
wrinkles, because they are
relevant to kind of consider,
but maybe don't think too much
about making sure you understand
all the details of it. Open
licenses have this distinction
between what we call copyleft
and non copyleft. licenses,
which basically have to do with
whether modifications of a work
have to be shared under the same
principles. The idea with the
copyleft licenses. So something
like the GNU Public License, the
GPL is that if someone writes a
piece of software and shares it
with that license, a company
can't just build off of that
software, and then sell their
modifications, they also have to
distribute their modifications
in the same license. And that
way, if there's a way of
ensuring that kind of, if you're
going to use something in the
copyleft world, that you also
contribute to that world. And
this is not true for licenses
that are permissive, but not in
the copyleft scheme. And we
generally prefer those in the
kind of open licensing world.
And I think for, you know, open
life science, we don't
necessarily want to be overly
restrictive with how people can
reuse our work. But that is if
that is something that is
important to you, that is
something to consider. The next
thing is that patents are also
not related to copyright, which
are not are not the same thing
as licensing. So copyright
rights include the ability to
copy, modify, and redistribute
work. And patent rights include
the ability to use make and sell
work. And so this generally
tends to come up when you're
talking about software, in that
open source licenses for
software may or may not
explicitly include something
that grants patent rights. And
this is a whole big can of
worms. So I'll just say if you
are writing software, and you
have a plan to patch the
software in any way, definitely
talk to a lawyer before thinking
before just slapping an open
license and expecting that your
patent rights will be preserved.
Okay, that was a lot. So let's
go into the the kind of details
of how you go about applying the
license. So a license file is
usually named license in all
caps, and it goes in the root
directory or the top most folder
of your project. And you can
definitely include multiple
licenses. And that's important
because you might have different
components of your project that
you want to apply different
licenses to. And that's kind of
important because licenses that
are best for software are not
ideal for content, like images
or writing, and in the reverse
as well. And so there are ways
that you can specify in the
license section of your README,
or the license file exactly
which parts of your project are
associated with which license.
So again, data and code and
creative works are not the same
thing. And so you may require
different licenses on here's an
interesting tweet I saw earlier
this week about this topic that
is relevant. And so ways that
you can add a license to your
project and GitHub, if you are
creating a new repository and
GitHub, there's a section at the
bottom where you can initialize
the repository by clicking that
checkbox.
And then you can choose a
license from among a number of
built in defaults to GitHub. So
that's a way you can just start
out a project with a license.
But if you already have a
project on GitHub, there's
another way you can add one of
these license templates. Which
is when you use the feature to
add a new file. If you start
typing the file name, license in
all caps, a button pops up,
which lets you choose a licensed
template. And that's also really
handy to have in that, again,
you don't have to go look for
the full text of a license and
get the file. If you're just
working in GitHub. Those are
built in defaults. Some useful
tools for exploring the
different possible licenses you
might want to use. creative
comments has a website that goes
through kind of the different
creative commons license says
including the CC zero public
domain license and the variants
of the CC by which include
requirements, for instance, for
attribution, or not letting
people create derivatives of the
work. Software, again is
different, there are different
licenses for software. So
hopefully, this table gives you
a brief guide to some of these
possible licenses. And then the
websites themselves have more
detailed information that are
useful for you. Again, more
resources, if you would like to
learn more about this very
complex legal Lee's topic in
detail. But I will just sum up
this content in that you if
you're building a open project,
and you want others to build off
of your work and use it, you
need a license. And that license
is going to be this top level
file whose name is license. If
you have code and data in
different content in your
project, you will want to use a
different license for those
different types of content. And
then some good permissive
defaults, if you're working with
code is to share a code using
the MIT license. If you are
sharing writing or documents or
images, the CC by license or for
data that you use the CC zero
license, which effectively puts
it into public domain