Unknown: Hi, everyone. So first
of all, let me just open this by
saying that I am not an agile
expert. These are just some
techniques that I that I tend to
use, often on my day to day.
And, and we will explain a
little bit what this is and how
you can benefit from using this.
So first of all, what is
ajl? So AJ was a bit of a
principle or a framework to to
organize and structure projects,
it's, let's let's, let's call it
a project manager, or project
project management technique.
If if you're one of these people
that tend to have a lot of posts
around with tasks to do, and so
on, you're probably already even
using some of the techniques
that the Agile movement
inspires.
But to perhaps keep it a bit
more focused on the point. So
agile is something that started
in industry,
it was mostly driven by an
intention to deliver a good
product to,
to the customers, but at the
same time to deliver that
product as quickly as possible,
even if in a prototype state.
But at the same time, allowing
to,
again, as quick as possible,
adapt and modify the product to
better fit the needs of the
client. And so as you can kind
of, you can kind of see from
from just the ajl software
development manifest. And this
was, as I said, was something
that started in the industry,
but specifically in the software
world. And, and the kind of like
striking point, and the reason
why it's called a jail is is in
part because of this. Want, I
don't know if you can see my
mouse cursor malvika? Can you
maybe give me a thumbs up? No.
Okay.
Then let's see if I can do
this.
Can you see it now?
Yeah.
So so what I was pointing to is
responding to change, this was
one of the aspects that
kind of motivated to give this
name to, to the movement or to
the framework, and a trial in
the sense of being very fast and
kind of responsive to, to
requests and changes. And so you
might, if you if you look a
little bit into what these, this
framework consists of, or if you
compare it with other kind of
approaches that people use in
the field,
you may encounter these these
words, waterfall. And you might
find also
other names for this kind of
iterative process. There's many,
many different ways that you can
structure this.
And I'll explain a few in in a
second. But if you just look at
the waterfall kind of concept,
you can, you can see that it it
falls from one stage to the
next. The key point here is that
all of the project plan is kind
of defined from the beginning.
And you just follow along in a
screen in a sequential fashion.
So you can imagine that, if at
any point during design, or at
any point during the
implementation, or one of the
later stages, there's something
that you need to change about
the plan. This process is rather
rigid and doesn't really allow
this. And so the iterative
process is a bit more generic or
a bit more responsive,
it typically starts by breaking
a larger problem into smaller
chunks, so that they become more
actionable. Exactly what small
means. This is what differs a
lot between different paradigms,
but it can be something that
lasts a day, it can be something
that lasts a few hours. And then
you you do these kinds of
sprints, or you aggregate these
tasks into milestones. And, and
once each milestone is
completed, then you reach a
stage where where you have like
a first release or a prototype
of the thing that you're trying
to accomplish. In the case of
your or less project, it can be
a milestone, for instance, you
have a website to build. And you
can think how to break the that
big task into smaller chunks.
And it could be the first
article that you write could be
the an example of a first
deliverable.
And so to sum it up, it's a
technique primarily for software
development, but we can use it
elsewhere. And we can go a
little bit more into detail of
how to actually do that. It's
it's great for product project
management, it helps you
visualize the work that you
still have to do, and also to
invite others to join the
project as well because
everything is very visible in
terms of what needs to be done
and what has been done. And then
there's lots that there's lots
of variations in terms of how
This is structured, and also in
terms of advantages over the
traditional waterfall method. So
So I mentioned breaking down
things into tasks and smart and
milestones and so on. And I
mentioned as well that you could
aim for slices of one to two
hours, ideally, not more than a
day or two. The reason for this
fragmentation is because you
want to have a good a good sense
of, of progress, it's very often
the case that you estimate a
task to be one or two hours. And
then it turns out to do spend an
entire afternoon or something
because we get distracted,
because there's other things
that we didn't really think. And
the idea here is that the Agile
movement will help you structure
those things that are outside of
the tasks that you're doing. And
they just become tasks again,
that will get picked up later,
and move to a milestone that you
will complete at a later stage.
And so to give you a more
concrete example, or a real life
example,
if if you have already explored
a little bit of GitHub, and if
you've perhaps browsed some of
the existing projects there, you
might see project like inter
mine, where in this in this
diagram, each of these gray
boxes is
sorry, for the background noise.
Each of these back each of these
gray boxes is a version release.
And the tasks themselves are
within each of these gray boxes.
And in this case, milestones,
there are several them, you can
see already some estimate of
when these would be achieved.
And, and, and also a very
colorful interface for for how
the how to label things and how
to structure not just in terms
of milestones, but also in terms
of what these tasks are, are all
about.
In a in a slightly different way
or a more
kind of so one of the cons, one
of the paradigms in a job or a
more popular one, if you've used
the Kanban style board where
instead of having
the versions like or the
milestones, as we mentioned
before, you have just the notion
of what what is to be done, what
is in progress and what is
already completed. So this is
like a simplified version is not
so focused on one software or
versions or specific milestones
or goals. But it's more to
capture what is actually being
active worked on. And and you
could do this process within a
milestone. So all of the tasks
that you now see in the screen
could be within one milestone
alone. This alters this, also to
say that for GitHub, there's
some simplifications and some
automation that you can do. And
you we can we can talk about
that later if you're interested.
And so just to wrap up some
examples, you could have a task
that is just to acquire like in
the website context that I
mentioned before, one, one big
task could be to acquire a
domain for that website. And
then you can see an example of
how to break that task down into
smaller tasks. Or if you have a
specific section of the website
that you want to create. And
then you can see that for that
there's perhaps more tasks that
need to be completed. And so
ideally, you would break it down
again, into into subsequently
smaller steps.
I will skip this for for the
sake of time. And I didn't go so
much into the jargon that is
involved, I mentioned that
there's different sub
frameworks, Scrum, Kanban. And
Extreme Programming are some
examples of these. They all
follow the the Agile principles,
what changes between them is
sometimes how big these tasks
are, how big the milestones are,
how often you you kind of do the
the larger loop or the smaller
loop for how long you do these
things called sprints, which is
kind of a way of getting the
entire group working
collectively in a set of tasks.
And, and then just how you
structure but so without going
too much into detail on that is
just different ways of handling
the workload and in prioritizing
the tasks that you have to do.
And, and then to finalize, even
though as I tried to be very
superficial here as well, to
kind of give a high level
introduction to this to this
topic. If you're if you're doing
software development, you will
find that all of this probably
translates a lot more versions,
milestones and so on. This kind
of makes sense. But I I use this
personally for it for my own day
to day just to manage tasks that
I have to do things like
reporting or planning meetings
or anything, anything of this
sort and and I find that it
works rather well.