Iratxe Puebla: That's a portal
Associate Director for as a
buyer, which is a non for profit
organization with a mission to
drive innovation and
transparency to life sciences
communication. We have a great
interest in supporting adoption
and awareness around preprints
in terms of how life sciences is
communicated, I was gonna
mention a little bit for
context, the activities that we
run around preprints. We
regularly run projects and
gather stakeholders together to
discuss the different elements
of the preferences, ecosystem,
water, which are there perhaps
upcoming challenges or subjects
that may require on developing
some principles or structures
etc. We also develop resources
are related to preference mostly
focus on providing information
for results so that they can
make informed choices when they
choose to prepare, but they're
also available to obviously any
stakeholder in life in life
sciences communication. And we
also run the ace of bio
community, which is an online
global community of mostly
researchers, but also some other
stakeholders, who also have an
interest in supporting again,
awareness and adoption of
preference. So we're here to
talk preprints, what's
appropriate, one of the
perennial common set of
questions and there is no common
definition or unique definition.
So I'm going to give you one
that covers quite a few of the
elements. Essentially, and many
of you may already be familiar
anyway with water, preprint, and
conferences. But a preprint is
generally considered a scholarly
manuscript that is posted by the
authors to a representative
repository or platform to
facilitate the open and broad
terrain of the early work
without limitations on access.
And a definition or description
that I quite like and I tend to
reuse is one that was mentioned
by young English with who is the
co founder of the preprint
servers by archive on mid
archive, who has to refer to
previous as the director's cut
of a manuscript essentially
assume that they also are happy
to share with our community and
our peers, knowing that perhaps
you may undergo changes they may
updated once they get feedback,
or it undergoes peer review. So
there are a number of elements
in that definition, and then how
we work with preprints. That may
sound very familiar to how we
publish articles and journals.
So I thought I would go very
briefly over some of the
similarities, but also how
preprints are different from
from journal articles. The
similarities is, as we said,
well, both articles and
preference report the scholarly
work. And generally again, some
preprint servers cover different
outputs. But generally a
preprint is the full paper with
all the information about the
study that allows others to
replicate it, to appraise it to
provide comments etc. preference
are generally assigned a DUI,
there are some exceptions to
this like archive who we use,
they use their own persistent
identifier system. But again,
the majority in the majority of
cases, they receive a DUI so
that they traced unfound. And
obviously, they can decide that
if you have use that in your
work, you can add a reference on
again, find that through the
DUI. However, there are also
differences between preprints
and publications and journals.
The most important is that the
preprint servers we take will
take the version of the paper
that you submit, generally, they
do some basic screening just to
take that instantaneous results
paper and there is nothing
hugely problematic. And they
will post the paper without peer
review. And a few other
differences that I saw there was
worth mentioning is that
preference allow versioning.
Again, the authors This means
that the authors can post a new
version again, make updates on
new work to their paper and post
a new version on the server and
link to this it means that
correcting the paper if you need
to correct it tends to be much
easier and faster than when you
publish a paper that you're not
aware enough to go through the
editorial process again. So they
decide how do they post a
correction what goes into it,
etc. So from that perspective,
that there is an element of ease
and fluidity to use in
preference. So why are results
of using choosing to use
preference. The first important
benefit of preference is the
fact that there is the speed of
the dissemination. They allow
you
to make the work available
almost immediately. If you're
familiar with the journal
publication process, you will
know that it can take weeks or
months and sometimes if it goes
wrong even years to essentially
go through the editorial process
until the journal will publish
the work make it publicly
available. And obviously
sometimes you may get rejected
and you have this myth or no
urinal and restart the clock
etc. By comparison, if you post
your paper to a preprint server,
it will be available In a matter
of days, generally, again,
depending on the screening
process, which means that you
have a record that you can sell
with your community and request
comments. And all of that can
happen very quickly. And you can
do it either before or in
parallel to also submit into
your notes. Another important
benefit of preferences is that
they are free to both post and
free to access, there is no
publication fee as you may have
found during open access. There
is no element of issues with
access they provide free access
there are not subscriptions or
paywalls, which means that you
can actually reach quite a wide
audience. A number of indexing
services such as Google Scholar
and European seer, actually
include certain preprints that
also provides visibility and
PubMed also, it now is running a
pilot related to COVID-19
preference. So you can reach a
wide audience, which is which
can also be useful in terms of
your work and garnering
attention for your study and
potentially attack more
citations, there's been a number
of studies that have looked at
the relationship between the
present of presence of a
preprint and the citations on
the dental journal publication
for the same work and they
consistently so that one there
is a prior associated preprint.
For the for that work. The
actual journal publication
attacks more citation. So say
you've given a header style to
other results has to build on
your work. And another element
that I wanted to mention that we
are very passionate about in
terms of preferences, this
element of allowing a non
community feedback, you can get
the link of your preference,
right with all the others in
your community request comments
that you can use to again,
perhaps build on your work,
revise your paper, improve it.
And it can also be an
opportunity to open in
collaborations with all those
because there may be other
groups who are working in a
similar line of results as you
and you can get, they may
contact you after seeing your
your preprint. And as something
that has happened recently is
that your notes have also taken
an interest in this. And some of
them have appointed editors who
say what's the latest papers
posted on preprint servers and
may even invite submission to
their journal. So you can
actually increase the
publication chances for your
event on your paper. And so I
wanted to spend a few minutes
giving a few tips in terms of
making the print print and
experience as positive as
possible. So just a few pointers
if you've decided to preprint
something a few of the things
that I would recommend thinking
about. The first one is to have
a little bit of a thing as to
which preprint server you would
like to post your paper to the
preprint server ecosystem is
different from yours and celadon
not 1000s and 1000s of pages of
servers necessarily, but there's
been quite a few new platforms
that have launched over the last
few years. And now specifically
for the life sciences, which is
again where we work there are
around 50 servers available. So
as is the one that I have is
that you take the ace of bio
preprint server directory will
have a list of the different
platforms with characteristics
that you can check and compare
to fit your needs. There are a
few you know porpoise
repositories that also take
apart from the fact that there
was set up to take for mostly
data sets and all the outputs,
they will also take a full
paper. So for example, center
lawn fixture and they will
assign the eyes as I say
explained earlier. One thing to
consider, as you're thinking
well to both obviously this is
your your choice. But if you
think that can be useful is to
try to think about what elements
are important for you in what
you want to get out of, again,
sharing your work as
appropriate. One possible
consideration is visibility. The
different servers have different
communities associated with
them. So some pay more attention
to certain servers, etc. So you
may want to think which is the
best server to for your
audience, for your paper that
also some, for example, funders
on again, indexing services that
have certain criteria
recommendations for the service
that they recommend. So you may
want to take that into account
if that's something that is
relevant for your work in terms
of submitting to a server that
fits the requirements from your
funder.
And as you are again, preparing
to submit You should also think
if you are eventually thinking
of also submitting to a urinal
check the urinal policy on
preference. The majority of the
urinals in the life sciences
accept work that has been posted
as preference but they may have
different policies in terms of
the type of preprint servers
that they accept or when they
are happy to see the paper
posted as a preprint compared to
the urinal submission. So that's
something useful to check out.
Add an important consideration
is also to think about the
license that you would like to
apply to your preprint. There
are a number of licenses
available, I list the resource
that we have on as a buyer
related to the Creative Commons
licenses. One thing to remember
is that certain preference areas
allow a variety of licenses you
can choose from while some
models actually restrict the
licenses. And actually, some all
will only post on the city by so
something that you should check
prior to post them. Right. So
once you have made your choice
in terms of the servers, you
obviously so prepare your
manuscript, be as careful as you
will be one submit into a
urinal, perhaps even more. But
one important element is of
course, it and this is the same
as when you submit to a urinal,
they usually have all of the all
sorts on board with pre printed
so make sure that you have that
conversation with your co
authors where again, we have a
number of resources on the ace
of buyer website that can help
with some of those conversations
or some questions that people
may have about pre printing. And
then obviously, we very much
support open science so we
recommend that you take steps to
also sell the data reagents or
tools that we've been just
discussing in the earlier
exercise you can add links to
that to your preference so that
the preprint can again be
available for for anyone
interested in your paper in your
work to also find the associated
outputs. Right. So once you have
done all of that, obviously go
ahead and post the preference
will be available again either
immediately if there is no prior
screening prior to posting or
yes in a matter of days and then
we very much say yes to a result
of that they take the
opportunity to encourage
feedback and and so their work
with us on social media or email
again try to kind of create the
bottom of the prepared and a
conversation going about your
work. And with that, I wanted to
stop there and you have my
contact details there and on the
on the agenda document or and I
also included here the link the
link to for the a survey
communities Would you be
interested in joining us with
some resources and we exchange
ideas or preference they also
You're very welcome to join us.
Thank you so much.