Unknown: Mountains of
engagement, this technique is
introduced to me by our very own
malvika. And I've since used it
at least five to six times
incredibly helpful for me to
structure my thinking around
community engagement and
pathways that an elder also
mentioned already. So I hope and
I think we're all aware of this
kind of management levels
within, you know, your typical
organization, you have members
and leaders with different
responsibilities and tasks, and
delegations and completion. And
there are also opportunities for
people to be get appraisals, to
get promoted to have more
leadership ability and feel
recognized for the work.
Similarly, you can imagine in
the community, this type of
structure do exists implicitly
or explicitly. And so it is
important for us to think a
little bit about, you know, how
people interact within your
community, the organization, the
project and its culture,
discover how people can move
between different types of
interactions and develop
pathways for people to move from
sort of first contact, which is
the lower level of engagement to
sustained engagement to
leadership. So, speeding through
this, you can construct your
mountain of engagement in five
steps, you start with a list of
all the people's interactions in
your work, this could be things
like, you know, following you on
Twitter, to writing a blog post
for your project, attending a
community call, list everything,
and then try and create bands of
engagement. So think about, you
know, whether how much time or
how much effort this takes how
engaged they are
correspondingly. And then group
these interactions into your
bands, and then give each of
them a name. So it could be like
first contact or sustained
participation to like the top
level five, there usually is
leadership. And then look at how
folks are moving between these
different levels, identify what
works and what doesn't work,
this is going to be a lot the
longest process, once you've
sort of, I would say it never
ends. Basically, once you've
constructed your mountain, you
constantly need to be asking
your community and you know,
sort of getting a sense of how
you can modify these so that
people can actually effectively
climb up the mountain, and use
that insight to prioritize your
work to create more
opportunities. So as I said,
I've gone through this really,
really quickly. The rest of this
slide deck has a lot of
questions that you can use to
ask yourself and your community.
So basically, do more of that
step four, and step five type of
work. But that's the gist. I
hope I give you a quick overview
of what's happening here. And
was this technique and was
useful for and if you have
further questions, you know,
please approach any of us
malvika, yo, Bernice and myself,
and probably others in the
cohort as well. And we're all
familiar with this technique.
Some sense. So I'm handing over
to Vera. Nice to talk about
welcoming new contributors to
projects.
Okay, thanks. So I will be also
short tried to be short. So
yeah, it's more a practical way
how you can welcome new
contributors and engage them and
empower them in your project. So
I will share some things. So and
then we're going to discuss
about so got the pathway here is
more on the mentorship side. So
you can monitor your
contributors to build the
pathways through their pores
through your project, from the
first interaction to
leadership's what sorry. So
first things is how you attract
contributors. So you created
pathways, but also, you can also
you need to document your
project to learn about README,
contributing. Five, the Code of
Conduct license one map are
really good to have particular
things you need to add to your
project. One of the things that
is really helpful to attract
contributors is to create small
tutorials on how to contribute
to your projects, lab value
issues on your GitHub
repository, share with GitHub or
Git lab repository or any other
to say which which issue shoe
could be easily certified by new
contributors. So you can like
label them newcomer friendly, I
pointed first time only first
timer only to be sure that this
issue are done by people that
are not are not so much familiar
with your project. Another thing
that is really helpful is to
organize collaboration events,
so or co fest where other people
can come and learn how to
contribute to your project and
they they have people that can
help them there. Then what is
good also is to when you have
new contributions is monitoring
your code tribution. So when
your new contributor comes,
there needs to it's good that
they have support on how to get
started, where to find the end
of clear requirements in each of
the issues. What are the
requirements for solving these
issues and point through
relevant information when
needed, so contributing
guidelines and others. And so
when a new contributor arrives,
it's really great if you could
welcome them and point to these
resources. So either you do it
manually for each of the
contribution, but you have also
some waken votes that you can
link to your GitHub repository
that could point that
automatically to the people. And
one of the things that is make
the commitment to respond to
inquiries, so it requires times,
but it's helpful for the people
that are not feeling that they
are doing the work for nothing.
And once they're contributed or
submitting pull requests, or
GitHub or on GitHub, thank them
for their work, because they did
something. And they take the
time to learn how to do that.
And it's really, yeah, I think
it's the most important things
give good, consistent and
helpful feedback during the
review. So both good. Positive
also, and also sometimes the
negative feedbacks is also
important. Ask questions about
what they have done guide them,
I like to work on your project.
So put them on GitHub or social
media, have a list of
contributors is also useful when
you way you can highlight the
contributors, even if it's just
fixing a small issue, there's
more I mean, small mistakes or
small out to say, yeah, small
things, buying them to a good
next issue task that they can do
for the that they can become
more and more. They can you can
empower them. And then you have
you can go to the next step. So
continuing moderation, so you
can continue, you can improve on
more and more your contributors.
So being available, what are the
time that what are much time
they have an hour they want to
you can you need to learn from
them that I will not go through
the details here because we are
really short in time, but you
have the detail there about what
you can do. provide ongoing
support. So monitor any channel
or channel that you have
uncertain any newcomers
questions, provide guidance and
guidelines connect people with
other members, because you are
not the only one that can guide
them or mentor them. There is
other contributors in your
project fully, and then they can
help others and organize really,
community events that are really
greatly great welcome.
supporting multiple new
contributors, for me, was really
the main things that I learned
from the different projects I'm
involved in.
establish clear expectations
pathway and, and personally, I
think it's a really great,
communicate regularly. So give
feedback to the to your
contributors. And, and yeah,
involve them also in in
different in the different
decisions that can be taken,
provides structure through the
review process and grage
constantly them and prove and
give them some more and more
leadership's then and model best
practices. And there are some
questions. So either an issue
you can start modeling today.
And do you need to set up a chat
channel or something where other
people could ask that question?
And should you model any of your
current contributors to take
more roles in your project? It
was really quick, but I think
you can learn a lot. I mean,
it's really it was really
helpful for me for my projects
to to to use to apply these
practices this small trick there
and get more people there.
Thanks. I mean,
yeah. Thank you very much. Very
nice. Yeah, sorry, flew through
that folks. Lots to digest. And
I'm also we're also one minute
over the hour ready. So if you
need to log off, please do now.
We have a couple of assignments
for you one of them mentioned
already by a nelda. There are
you know, if you can complete
some personas and pathways,
ideally with your community
together, then that will be
awesome. Fantastic. If not, you
know, I guess the most important
thing actually, we'd like you to
do is to think about your
presentations and graduation. We
have next week three rehearsal
calls, I think Tuesday,
Wednesday and Thursday. The
Times are in the calendar. you
need you need to I think put
your name down for one of them.
Check your email. Thank you.
Well, you can check your emails
for further instructions and
details. If anything is on
Clear, just give us a shout on
slack Lowe's to read from this
call. So I hope you can, you
know, take the time to do it.
And again, we're here. So let us
know if you have any questions
or if there's any thoughts and
comments that you'd like to
share after. All right. Thank
you. Um, hope to see you all
next week. Thank you so much to
our guest speakers and everyone
for attending.