Alex Holinski: My name is Alex. I work
as a scientific training officer
at EMBL-EBI, so the European
bioinformatics Institute in the
UK, and as a scientific training
officer, well, what do I do? I
work together with scientific
experts and bioinformaticians
to develop, organize and run
bioinformatics training courses.
I, I'm training as you see, I
also am used to prepare training
material. I also support
others and preparing training
material and sharing the sand.
Yeah, this is why I'm here to
talk about FAIR training now.
Well, why should you actually
care about sharing your
training, material sharing
training material can have a lot
of benefits. And there are a lot
of reasons for sharing it. For
example, other people who will
look for the training material
online, they can use it as a
sole source for self study, and
gain a lot of new knowledge from
this. But not only for trainees,
it can be beneficial, but also
for trainers, they can use the
training material they find
online as a source of
inspiration. They can even reuse
the training material and edit
it and build upon it, which can
save them a lot of time and
money. But also trainers who put
their training material online
and can get a lot of
recognition, of course. So this
all sounds great. But when we
look for training material
online, either as trainees
because we needed for self-study,
or we are looking for
something as a source of
inspiration, as in the in the
role of a trainer, we know that
a lot of questions can occur. So
for example, and we might
wonder, well, where can we
actually find suitable training
material? And if we have found
that we might want to when was
it written? Is it still up to
date? Or Who wrote it? I still
have more questions about the
content. can I contact anyone?
Or another question might be in
which context was context was
the training material presented?
And another important question
is, can I actually reuse the
training material material? Am I
legally allowed to do so. So you
see that a lot of questions can
pop up. And this is why it's so
important if you're sharing from
my training material to do that
in a FAIR way. So in a way that
it is findable, accessible,
interoperable and reusable.
applying the principles of
training materials provides a
framework for enabling and
sharing and about and thereby
helping train us to make the
most of the material but also
help them train us to get
trainees to get the most
efficient learning experience.
So now, how can we make training
material FAIR, so there was a
very great publication, which
gives an overview of 10 simple
rules for tracking, making
training materials FAIR and in
the following, I will now run
through these 10 rules. And at
the, in the very last minutes of
my talk, I will also very
quickly show you how we at EMBL-EBI
apply these guidelines to our
training. So how can you make
your training materials more
fIndable? First, you have to
describe it properly. And by
doing so, or you should do so by
annotating it with structured
metadata as of data which
describes your material. And,
for example, bio schema is an
initiative which facilitates the
addition of metadata to life
science resources, and this
helps to make it more findable
online. And you should also
annotate it with keywords using
structured controlled
vocabularies. And I will give a
more concrete example of this.
At the very end, we'll refer
back to this at the very end of
my talk. Also, you should give
it a unique identifier attaching
and persistent identifier to
your training material makes it
more easy to track online, but
also will help you to be able to
or will make it citable. And
you can also assign a persistent
identifier to the author. And we
have already heard about your
ORCID, which simply helps to
identify the the author
unambiguously online. Of course,
you should also add your
training material to an online
repository so that other people
know that it exists. And these
repositories can be
institutional ones, but they can
also be open once this can be
general once or more more field
specific ones we have already
heard some, for example,
Zenodo, which is a more general
one. And in the bioinformatics
field, we for example, have
"ELXIRE Tess"
is the life science training
portal where you can find a lot
of bioinformatics and life
science training material.
Well, how to make your training
material accent more accessible
by making it finable in a
repository and assigning a
persistent identifier to it you
already are nearer to the target
to make it more accessible for
others. But then the
accessibility of training
material can vary for different
reasons. There might be
material, which is more
restricted, where the access is
more restricted because it's for
example, only accessible for
specific If members of a
university or payment might be
required, all training material
can be completely open. It's
always very important to clearly
and state clearly define how
people can access the material.
And even maybe also do this in
plain English so that there is
absolutely no confusion of how
people and can access it so that
it will be simply more and be
more accessible by being
transparent about this. Well,
how can you make your training
material more interoperable, and
when you share training
material, you should always keep
in mind that other people might
want to reuse it might to edit
it might want to build upon it.
And you also have to consider
that other people might want to
use the training material across
different computational systems,
or might even want to use it
offline. So you have to balance
them carefully which format
you want to take for your
training material. For example,
if you give a presentation, and
you think about presenting it in
PowerPoint format, well, this is
always very helpful. If because
people are trainers can edit
this very easily and can build
upon it. If you For example,
compare this with a PDF format,
which is not so easily editable,
but then a PDF form but is, of
course, much more easily usable
across different computational
systems. So you have to
carefully consider this when you
deliver training. Well, how can
you make your training even more
reusable, it's very important
that you assign a license to
your training material. So this
will allow other people's to
know if they are allowed to read
that and how they are allowed to
use that. And also tell them how
materials should be cited when
they reuse it. Also add more
metadata to describe the context
of the material. And that's
helped the trainers to get more
information about your material.
This should for example, include
when was the material written
and Who wrote it? Where was it
presented, in what context and
what was the trade at the target
or the audience of the event and
portfolio learning outcomes of
this event. Also, keep your
training material up to date,
and clearly state when it was
last updated, and also welcome
contribution. So encourage
others to provide feedback and
contribute to the further
development of your material. So
I have given you now a lot of
guidelines, in theory. And in
the following and last few
minutes, I would very quickly
like to show you how we apply
these guidelines and for our
training that we deliver, or
that we provide at EMBL. So
first, we, as I've already told
you, we offer bioinformatics
training. And our training is
comprised of life and training
courses, which are face to face
courses, not at the moment, of
course, but also virtual courses
and life seminars. And we also
have on demand training. So
online training, like online
tutorials, recorded webinars,
and course materials and you can
access and find every all of our
training offer on our course web
page, we made the following
error very quick, very more
refer to the online tutorials we
have. So we describe our online
materials properly by for
example, using EDAM Ontology so
EDAM Ontology is a set of
controlled vocabularies, which
describes concepts which are
very common in methods and
computational biology. We also
link the EMBL-EBI resources, so
the databases that are covered
in the training tutorials, to
the tutorials, and we also
describe them, I'm using extra
terms and keywords which
describe the topics of the
tutorials by this, we aid the
search and to search
autocomplete function on our
page. We also give unique
identifiers to our tutorials.
For example, you can see here
that we have a DOI. And with
this digital object identifier,
we make this tutorial citable
by others, and also our authors
they have ORCID assigned to
them. So they are also
unambiguously identifiable. We
also make our material reusable,
we have licenses assigned to our
material. We for example, I'm
used to CC-BY SA license, which
allows other people to use our
material to transform it and
rebuild on it. But they should
give us credit and also share it
under the same license again.
We also keep our training
material up to date, we keep it
up to date or we review it once
a year and we clearly states on
the page on the web page when it
was last updated. What is now
not shown here is that we also
asked our trainees for feedback.
So we use standard feedback
forms where we really encourage
people to let us know what I
think about our training
material and to give us some
helpful feedback so that we can
revise it and regularly so all
in all, I should say this is all
work in progress so we still can
make our training and much more
FAIRer. Because it's a long
process to really make it very
FAIR. And I'm For example, we
are working on adding further
metadata texts on to our
material and also expanding the
our materials just
to name a few examples with this
idea. And I've also provided
some more helpful resources. I
have included the paper here to
the 10 simple rules. And then
there are also two webinars
where you can which you can
watch where you can find more
information and I will also add
them to the to the living
document, which is provided. So
if we have time for questions,
and if there's any questions,
I'm happy to receive them and
otherwise, you can always of
course, also contact me for my
email address or find me on
LinkedIn.