Emma Anne Harris: I'm Dr Emma Anne Harris.
And I've worked in research
integrity research ethics, open
science, responsible research
kind of area for a number of
years. And I used to give
training workshops on on Open
Science, including data for
several years in my last
project. So that's kind of how
I'm here today. So I just want
to quickly go through a few
things. And I think I'm touching
on a few things that my fellow
speakers are going to talk about
as well, such as training and
software. So I'll, I'll move on
from those quite quickly,
because I didn't want to take up
space when you've got people who
have more expertise. But I'm
very quickly going to start with
a FAIR data analogy that I use
in training, this helps I think,
just get us moving from the the
abstract terms to something a
little bit more concrete. And
also, if you are thinking of
doing any training yourselves,
it's a nice, nice thing to use.
Then I'm going to talk about
impediments and solutions. So I
didn't want to just kind of
reiterate a lot of the
information that's already out
there, but maybe move the
conversation a little bit
forward in terms of kind of
where we are now. And instead of
I mean, you could call it
impediments and solutions or
challenges and successes. And
then looking maybe at a little
bit of FAIR guidelines of what
we could kind of do more of what
some some ways we could could
manage FAIR data could be. So
just straight on with the I
don't know if you can see the
last image, let's move this
down. So the FAIR data analogy.
So there's a YouTube link in the
bottom right corner, you can
watch me give the whole thing in
detail. And you're welcome. Of
course, if you do find it useful
to embed it in any kind of
online courses, it's completely
CC-BY , but the way it
works is I, when explaining it,
I talk about data as treasure.
So if you imagine you heard
about some hidden treasure, you
know, like, you know, pirate
thing or something. And first of
all, you need to be able to find
the treasure, if you need a map,
you know, you need to be able to
find it. And then if you knew
where it was, you need to be
able to get to it. So are there
shark infested waters? Are there
bandits? Are there, whatever?
And then if you found a treasure
chest, could you actually would
you have the right key? It's no
good if you've got, say a Yale
modern key, and it's an old key
or vice versa? So could you
actually get get into the
treasure chest? And then when if
you got into the treasure chest?
Would the treasure be something?
Would it be crisp euro notes? Or
dollar note? Or would it be some
weird old money with skulls on
it? Which is not very useful to
anyone? And so yeah, I just use
this analogy just to get us
thinking maybe you know, a
slightly more dynamic way about
what FAIR actually means what
the individual parts of the FAIR
acronym actually stand for. And
I find this can be quite useful
to make it a bit more. Yeah, a
bit more real. So yeah, that's
just to kind of warm us up. And
now some of the little bit more
policy side of things a little
bit more in depth. So
impediments or I guess you could
also look at them as challenges.
Um, so the first one that I
think needs mentioning is the
inadequate storage and
inadequate repositories for
large, sensitive or discipline
specific data. So for instance,
I know that the Earth Sciences
often complain that they don't
feel they have a repository that
fully meets that data
requirements. So because
obviously, that that's got some
quite specialist requirements,
and you wanted to be storing
data in a very, very specific
way. And so generic depositories
aren't aren't really working.
And so that's, you know,
immediately you've got to think
about not just, when you're
thinking about FAIR data, you're
not just thinking about the FAIR
principles, you're also the data
part of that FAIR data. And in
order to make data FAIR, there
needs to be sufficient technical
support for the variety of data
that research data that's being
produced. You've also got things
like very large data sets, when
I was doing training, I'd often
hear this from researchers
saying, okay, but you know, I'm
looking at terabytes upon
terabytes of data. And they
simply there aren't repositories
that can handle that. And then
sensitive data. So You know, as
I said, I've worked on data
governance, data ethics. And you
know, you obviously I'm sure
you're all aware can't just be
putting personal medical data
in, Zenodo, there's no doubt.
So balancing FAIR and Ethical
Treatment of data is, you know,
I could give an hour long
presentation just on that. But
obviously, I just want to flag
it up as something to think
about when we're talking about
FAIR data. So moving moving on,
discipline, differences in
output in terms of impacting
interrupt ability. So
interdisciplinary
interoperability, try saying
that when you're drunk, is, is,
is a big issue. So particularly,
with the social sciences and the
humanities, you've got just
different terms, different
terminologies, or you've got
different attitudes to
persistent identifiers. so
ORCID, I had my ORCID ID up at
the start, but that's
not necessarily something all
disciplines are asking their
researchers to do. So that you
have these these gaps, if you
like, in terms of findability.
And, yeah, different levels of
outputs, and, and you know, how
things how variables are coded,
can really impact
interoperability. And I think
it's also important to note
that, you know, interoperability
is often somewhat forgotten,
it's probably the hardest of the
FAIR data principles to get
right. Findable is often the
most, the easiest, and it's the
one people start with. But, you
know, interoperability is is the
most difficult to to to define,
and it's the most difficult to
put into practice. So I think
that's very much worth worth
flagging. So those are kind of
some technical challenges. Then
you've also got some more, maybe
we'll call them social
challenges. So as I'm sure the
wonderful organizers of open
life science with a test, there
are plenty of solutions at a
community level. But the the
sustainability of those
solutions is often difficult,
because the you know, the
funding isn't there, people are
doing these things as side
projects. And that is impacting
the ability of FAIR data to just
become data. And that's the goal
right? At the end, we want FAIR
data to just be data. And then
the final thing is a lack of
legal or licensing knowledge.
And this obviously relates to
the art of fair, usable. And
the link, the hyperlink I've
got in the slides leads to
research by a colleague and
friend of mine. That's not why
LinkedIn, she's just very good.
But she's done work on on
research on how the concerns
about, say, GDPR and other legal
aspects of data reuse and
sharing, often hold researchers
back from making their data FAIR
from making it findable and
accessible. Because they they're
not sure how to navigate and
there isn't enough first level
support within universities,
about the legal issues. And then
you've got your classic fear of
scooping out, which I think
we're all kind of familiar with.
So yeah, solutions or successes.
So it has become more easy,
easier and more normal to cite
data and to create data as as a
publication. It's definitely
anecdotally and also there is
some evidence for this. I
haven't actually put a reference
here, because it's the the
report I read is still under
embargo. But yeah, it's the most
recent surveys are definitely
showing that it is becoming
normalized. So support from
repositories. So you've got the
"Core Trust Seal", and I'm not
sure how many of you are
familiar with that. But
essentially, it's something that
repositories can acquire, to
show that they are a reliable
repository where you can put
your data, but the core trust
seal requirements map quite
closely on to the FAIR data
principles. And so in, in in, in
getting the quarter seal, they
are actually meeting FAIR
requirements, which is obviously
a big success and big step
forward. Then you've got things
like virtual research
environments, I've given an
example run by the quest Center,
which is here in Berlin. And
this is where researchers it's
kind of what it sounds like.
Probably some of you are far
more familiar of it than I but
it's, you know, essentially a
place of work. short space where
researchers can create work on
research together. This,
obviously is is massively
helpful towards FAIR data
because it's all the data is
being worked on together,
sometimes interdisciplinary.
And the trouble with that,
though, there is a kind of
downside, the danger of that is
that you end up with these VRS
silos so that no one else who
wasn't originally in the virtual
research environment can then
reuse that data. So that's the
slight danger of that. Also, the
expectations and support by
funders and institutions are
changing. And, you know, data
management plans, which often
involves some aspects of the
FAIR principles, though not
enough, are becoming very
normal, unexpected. And
institutions are moving somewhat
towards having, you know, data
training and open data ideas.
So what could be FAIRer? What
could be more FAIR, I've
mentioned software here, but I'm
not going to to say anything
more on that, because I know,
one of my fellow speakers is
going to talk at more detail.
But just that, you know, while
open source kind of led the way
in terms of openness, generally,
there are inconsistencies in
terms of, of software being fair
services. So this is two fold.
First of all, you have could
services incorporate FAIR more,
if you imagine, say a library
giving data training, could
those services talk more about
FAIRness? And, and helping
researchers understand the FAIR
principles, but also that the
service themselves? Are they
FAIR? So is the training
recorded? Is it find about is it
accessible? You know, can it be,
you know, can be downloaded,
and, you know, my and in terms
of accessibility, we often mean,
sort of technical accessibility,
but also we should think about
accessibility in terms of, of
disability. And I noticed, you
know, you're using the Otter.ai
transcript. So that this this,
what, you know, this meeting
today is more accessible. And I
ran a podcast for several years
on open science, and, you know,
in to, you know, out of
ignorance, and just, I guess,
just not not, yeah, ignorance,
we didn't often provide a
transcript for that, which meant
that people who had hearing
disabilities couldn't access
that information, which is, you
know, it's not, it's not the
right, it's not best practice.
And it did limit the
accessibility of that
information. So there's a
project, if you click on the
link that is looking at FAIR
assessment, and how services and
service providers can make that
self assessment on whether
things are FAIR. And then
finally, just workflows, they
could be more FAIR, some things
towards that, as you know,
obviously, my experiment,
where you can kind of it's a bit
like a open notebook type thing.
And then persistent identifiers,
obviously, are helpful with
seeing where people are, and
sharing that workflow very
quickly. And I'm running low on
time. The other side of this
making things FAIRer compliance.
So this is a checklist, you
know, as to whether things have
been FAIR, and this is really
useful in just in terms of, you
know, using it with your own
projects, looking at whether
you've, you've made things FAIR,
so if you're doing any training,
it's it's it's very useful. But
obviously, you know, it could be
used in a very soft way, like as
a checklist. Or it could be used
by funders, you can imagine a
very kind of strict way, like,
have you done each of these
things? If not, you're not going
to get your money sort of way.
And then metrics, I put an
metrics question mark, and
there's a report there, which is
very interesting. I do recommend
you take a look at that.
Obviously, I think we're all
very wary of metrics given where
that's landed us in the
publishing industry. But FAIR
metrics might be a way forward.
And it's something that I think
funders and people like the
European Commission are going to
be very keen on very policy
minded people are going to like
that. So it's something maybe to
have an idea about, in general.
So I've got some further reading
links. They're also in the the
original document. And yeah,
there's there's links to contact
me. So I'll stop talking. I'm
not sure I am for time. I'll
take any questions. If there's
time for that, if not happy to.
You know, do that via writing.