Neil P. Chue Hong: My name is Neil Chue Hong,
I'm director of something called
the software Sustainability
Institute. And I'm based at
University of Edinburgh. And I'm
also involved in a group, which
is developing fair principles
for software. So this is part of
the research software Alliance,
the research data Alliance and
the FORCE11 groups, they're
going to be talking a little bit
about what FAIR means in the
context of software, and then
giving you some possible advice
to follow on how you can make
your software FAIR. One of the
things we've noticed in this
last year is that lack of access
to different things to data to
people to resources makes
research more difficult. But
this is something that's been
going on for a long time, I
often use this quote from the
creator of a piece of software
called PyMOL, because it's way
back in the early 2000s. He was
talking about the challenges to
effective research because of
the lack of access to software.
And he was one of the pioneers
of, of research software being
open, and transparent, and
reusable are all of the things
which are the principles of
FAIR. One thing is that
increasingly, the research
community relies on software. So
we did some work at the software
Sustainability Institute now,
seven years ago, it's it's crazy
to think it's seven years ago
now, where we were polling
people to find out how much
software effective their work.
And I think the key thing that
came up for us is that even back
then, there was about 70%, of
researchers who said it wouldn't
be practical to conduct their
work without using software. So
software is everywhere. It's
everywhere in each part of the
research lifecycle, from the
software you use to start
planning your experiments or
your research or to generate
ideas for research, collecting
and capturing different
information from data from
experiments, but also things
like references and other
reading material, organizing and
storing it, backing it up,
interpreting and analyzing it,
publishing it, and making sure
that it is available for others
to discover and reuse. So
software is everywhere. But it's
often not treated in the same
way as other types of research
output. And that's, that's
interesting, because the FAIR
principles are not just for data
in the original FAIR guiding
principles paper. There's this
line that says all scholarly
Digital Research objects from
data and analytic pipelines, to
benefit from the application of
the FAIR principles. So what
they're saying is that FAIR is
is important because you need to
be able to have trust in the
research process, you need to be
able to ensure that there's
transparency, reproducibility,
and reusability. So how does
software fit into this? The
challenges that software is not
just data. So if you look at it,
from a purely theoretic point of
view, software is just a special
subset of data. But in practice,
the way that it's used means it
needs to be treated differently
from data. And the third
principles applied in a slightly
different way. So there's some
things that are similar. Both
data and software are not
commonly cited. You can assign
identifiers like DOI to both of
them, you often have multiple
versions that exist, that might
be incrementally changing, or
they might be very different.
And the reuse of both software
and data is typically controlled
for licenses. There are some
things which are at one level
quite similar. But when you look
at the details are a bit
different. So the way that you
build on software and data and
link them together. Obviously,
we do that with both software
and data. But quite often, it's
different. So software tends to
be in the middle of the of the
sort of tree of a research
workflow, whereas data tends to
be at the edges of it. In both
cases, it may depend on hardware
and, and software. So the data
that's generated might be
dependent on the sensors, for
instance, or the experimental
machinery. And likewise, the
software may depend on the
machines that you're working on.
And in many cases, it's replaced
by newer alternatives. So the
evolution of both software and
data means that except in
particular fields, you'll always
have new things coming along
with similar or better
functionality that can be
swapped into the work they do.
But there are also a number of
differences. They are important
when we consider FAIR for
software. And the key ones are
that software typically has a
larger number and more complex
set of dependencies. So the way
that it changes over time is
more dramatic, you'll find that
software is isn't reusable, much
faster, and also that the reuse
might come in a lot of different
flavors. So when we think of
reuse of data, we're typically
thinking of the same way that
another person would have used
the data in the past. The only
difference might be if it's
being used in a different field,
or for a different problem, it's
still being used in the same way
generally. Whereas for software,
we might be thinking about
rerunning or, or executing the
software, we might be thinking
of reading it to understand the
decisions and the design
decisions in the software, we
might be using it to reproduce
an experiment, or we might be
reusing it through extending or
deriving something from it. So
reuse for software has a much
wider set of options then for
data in general. And it can also
be connected via workflows. And
there we have challenges for
FAIR, because the FAIR data
principles, although they talk
about interoperability, they
talk mostly around
interoperability of formats,
whereas for software, we're also
talking about interoperability
of API's, and interoperability
of semantic understanding as
well.
So
how is this evolved, the fair
guiding principles were
developed and finally published
in 2016. And over the last few
years, the community has been
exploring what it means to make
software FAIR. So we've had a
number of different workshops
run by different groups,
including some of the people who
are attending this call, looking
at how FAIR might be applied to
software. And this has resulted
in a number of different things.
In 2020, there are a large
number of different resources
published, where the community
was putting down its thoughts
about how FAIR should be applied
to software, including a paper
called towards FAIR principles
for research software, but also
tools that some of which are
referenced later on about how
you might see how FAIR your
software is. And understanding
this, the way that FAIR is used
in practice for software. And so
this has led to the
establishment of the FAIR for
research software Working Group,
which I'm a co chair of. And at
this moment, in fact, we have
the second last of our drafting
meetings tonight, we are looking
at drafting a new set of FAIR
principles for research
software, which will be going
into community consultation. So
the way forward after this is
the publishing of these
principles and getting community
feedback and approval on them.
But then it's going on with to
understanding all the other
things that happen once you have
the FAIR principles. So how
does that feed into things like
indicators and metrics into
career profiles and reward
structures, making it machine
readable in output management
plans and ultimately changing
policy to ensure that research
is more transparent,
reproducible and reusable. So
this is this is kind of like all
background information, but
you're probably interested in
knowing what you can actually do
right now. So I'm just going to
finish off with one slide on
what I think is good enough
practices for FAIR software
whilst you're waiting on us to
finish off the principles. So,
to make your software, findable,
make sure it's easy to
discover by using descriptive
metadata. So things like making
sure that it's got a descriptive
title, making sure that people
can understand who the authors
are providing keywords, publish
a citation for your software, so
people know how they should
credit you, and add it to a
community registry if one
exists. And I'll admit that
that's one area that a lot of
communities don't have a
community registry yet. To make
it accessible. Put your source
code in a code repository. So
something like GitHub is a good
choice there. And then deposit
major versions and activation
repositories. So if you're
publishing something that you
expect to be shared with someone
else, or it's in relation to a
paper, make sure it's going into
your institution's digital
repository, or into something
like Zenodo or Figshare to get a
DOI. Make it interoperable by
making sure you describe the
functionality of your software.
Use open data formats that meet
domain relevant community.
Standards provide references to
other research objects like
papers and the datasets that
you're using. And modularize
your code and documents design
so people understand how they
can connect it to other things.
And finally, to make your
software reusable, choose a
license and apply it to your
software. There's nothing worse
than a piece of software where
people can't understand how to
reuse it, document the
dependencies that's required.
And ensure that others can
understand and execute your
code. And often think the best
way of doing that last thing is
just give it to one of your
colleagues or friends to try and
rerun if they can't rerun it.
And that might be either by
building the source code, or by
running the executable or by
using the binder or Docker
container, then go back and have
a look at it because it probably
means that you won't remember
how to reuse it in six months
time either. So these are all
what I would consider good
enough practices for research
software. And I think the key
thing here is I I'm a pragmatic
implementer of FAIR principles.
I think it's all about making
sure that you're doing things
better and incrementally getting
better. And so I would say if
you can do any of these things,
then you're on the road towards
FAIR software. And if you're
interested in getting involved
in FAIR research software, I
put some information in the
slides and you can find out more