Zulidyana Rusnalasari: My name is Zulidyana
Rusnalasari, you can call me
Lydia or Jana, I'm a public
relations official have their
own general Indonesia is
nonprofit organizations to help
together people and sharing
their knowledge. And what we are
different from the others
nonprofit organization, because
actually, when we started, we
don't know much about journal
publications, academic
publication, and so on. We're
growing together, learning and
sharing and updating all the
time. That's why I, in the
title, I call it, it's a never
ending learning because we
always do the learning process
from the beginning of the
organization. And until now. So
first of all, I will tell you
about the story about Indonesia
during this five years. So we
have to make up publishers, in
journals, and academies. There
are several very big publishers,
they really dominate almost all
subjects. Even in Indonesia,
even we have the language
barriers. So as you know that
English is not my native
language, I am Indonesians. But
because I learned English
literature, and so on. So I can
overcome those language barriers.
So pardon me if my English is
not really good. But I will try
my best to explain you about the
stories of about
puplishers in Malaysia. We lack
sources. And we also lack
support. That's why it's
like we, we were in 2016, we
started this organization, like
some people in a dark room. And
we have to some people in the
tap room, and we close our eyes.
So even when our eyes just
opened, we still cannot see
anything. That's why we have to
make the light itself by
sharing. So this picture is
created by Mr. Irwin, that will
be present next week. Our local
and national publisher is just
like this, and we are surviving
until now. And we are still
growing and the number of
journals in Indonesia is growing
very fast. And this is not all
journalism, Indonesia is about
business. But mostly we share
because we want to participate.
So that started in 2016. There
were changed in government
regulation in scientific
publication for from printed to
online. So they gather people's
gather information from
trainings and meetings. But
sadly at the time, those
trainings and those meetings are
very expensive. We have some
organization that already well
literally about this academic
publishing, but they are so
explosives. So we have to spend
more than in a very big amount
of money. But the institution is
fairly diverse. Small
institutions also have journal
publishing, so they cannot
afford to join the trainings and
meetings. That's why in 2016, we
started these organizations.
Some general managers from
across Indonesia gather and
start the idea to build an NGO,
the nonprofit want to educate,
this is not meaning that we will
advocate it now but we started
in a very basic level of
knowledge support academic
publishing show. We are building
a community. We have the general
managers along with also center
viewers.
And in 2007 and 2020. When we
when we launch our one of our we
will launch one of our or
publications, a program. We have
these pictures from outside the
organization. So Mr. Edward is
drawing this. But actually, he's
not part of our organization.
But he was saying that, as an
organization, we have the
skills, we have the knowledge,
and we have the public support.
That's what power us, because we
want to say, have research that
really engaging to all people,
not only for those in academia,
but also for society. And it
also can influence the
government in the long run. But
the potential that we have in
the corners of Indonesia, in the
corners of 1000s, of islands,
Indonesia, so has already known
by peoples not only from the
academy publication, but also
for all people that becomes, for
example, like teachers, or
lecturers, students, even those
who are claiming themselves as
researchers, because we have a
challenge that when we read
about sources, mostly sources
are in English. But actually the
sources that already in our
country haven't published yet.
So the language barrier becomes
a homework for us. But we
dealing with that, because many
of people's in, in the
organizations are volunteer,
they are giving their time,
they're giving their energy, and
they're also giving the ideas to
building up this nonprofit
organization. So if we talk
about open science in Indonesian
journals, technically,
practically, mostly because we
are using VGS as the platform by
big IP, but the openness itself
actually started because we are
volunteers that getting
together, we are growing for
only bunch of people. Now we
have more than 200 volunteers
around Indonesia, in Turkey, in
in four, sorry, Indonesia has 34
provinces. So in each provinces,
we have representations
representative person, who
manage to be the person, the P
IC person, that probably if
people need help, can come back
this person, if this person
cannot afford to help them, they
can come back us in, in the
center of Indonesia to to come
to the cities or they're found.
We work together to assist, you
know, managers, this is very
challenging, because not all
people it's very limited people
in Indonesia that has computer
illiterate, they also have the
language barrier. So technical
problem, internet connection,
and also, the literacy becomes
our problem. At first in during
three years. We start our
training by building awareness,
why academic publication is
important for us. Why writing in
academic way is important. Why
people have to read why. So
those basic ideas and skills are
everywhere. It's just like a
very big homework for us. But
this community now become a
place to find answers because we
have a platform, we build a
platform that people can
register lock in and
asked because those 200
volunteers already there to
answer the question for our
around Indonesia so they can
drop the questions. We answer we
also provide a YouTube tutorial.
We also provide facts, examples
and so on. In many sources. We
also use zenodo to let's say
keeping our documents so
everybody can access. Very, we
also have I said before coffee,
it Usually we also going places
in Indonesia to have training,
meeting them face to face and
train them how to manage a
journal, academic journal,
provide even and mostly free of
charts because now during
coffee, all of them are online.
So these events is regularly
like, once in a week. Sometimes
we do it once in two days for
like salaries. For example, like
we collaborate with the oaG. We
collaborate with them. So we
can, let's say, having salaries
of training. The best line that
makes us always drawing is
culture of sharing. Because this
sharing even the knowledge is
very limited in one person, but
we share it and this part of
little knowledge that we have,
and and then it's also join with
the others people that also
probably just read our
knowledge, those little
knowledge becomes the mountain
of knowledge Academy, a
researcher, librarian, etc.
Everyone, everyone who concerned
about academic publication
journals. Usually they becomes
our big supporters. And we
collaborate to grow LTE, US
Indonesian dinar fowl and
Association, because we are a
nonprofit organization. But
concern is more in management,
the scientific journals in a
niche gap. And to support it, we
collaborate with our kids. We
have a good number of our kids,
and four of the crossref
ambassadors from Indonesia, our
energy volunteers, including me
becomes the concept ambassadors.
And we also building a good
network with lippie lippie is
Indonesian instead of Sciences
is a government Institute of
sciences to the UN. For this
collaboration, we developed what
we call a journal stories that
AI This is the platform still in
building. I mean, it hasn't
launched yet, because we plan to
launch this platform in June in
this June 2021. This platform
becomes a hub between scientific
journal manager scientific
journal Management Association
and scientific associations. So
to that we have a different
point of view here in Indonesia.
Because we don't, we don't
actually we don't feel
comfortable with the link from
scimago, for example, because we
don't really comfortable with
that. We create our network by
also bringing up the scientific
associations. So the ones that
we believe that those people in
associations in scientific
Association are people can let's
say they can charge whether this
journal has to improve in what
way? Is it a good journal? Or is
it journal that need to improve
improvement? We are not saying
any bad journals, because we
don't have any blacklisted
journals. Now, we are concerning
about improving not
blacklisting, including and
excluding indexing. That's not
our main goal, because we build
ourselves from scratch. So we
want everyone's to know
managers, reviewers, our users,
they are keeping the quality as
a community along with a
scientific Association.
So the upsetness of course,
pragmatic people around
Indonesia, there are so many
pragmatic people they get the
there are also some people
becomes mafia publication. They
provide instant publication and
ethical practice of publication.
And the second big obstacle is
the culture of writing. In
addition, people have a culture
of speaking and telling stories,
but they're not really good in
writing. Actually, writing is
one of our biggest obstacle. To
get in touch with the publishing
in Academy, and the obstacles is
the competition among education
institution, for me, because I,
you know, there are so many
competitions, because of the
rank, and that make us compete
most. But most of the ways
actually the sometimes it's not
appropriate. That's why in
journal stories later, we don't
have any rank. But we have
stickers and labels just like we
are doing in games. And into in
2020 mga as a nonprofit
organization, but we can become
the bronze sponsor for it, we
have more than 10 people becomes
associate editors. And we have
also three people becomes
editors into it, this is our
milestone to participate in open
science work light. And edgy
also become the biggest
processor affiliation in the
world. Because even we started
as community, we, we be, we we
help more than 5000 journals in
Indonesia and outside Indonesia,
that publice from 1500 local
properties is so we becomes the
number is getting high and high
because Institute's almost all
education institutions, building
their own journals publication.
Sometimes, probably, this is
bad, but actually we do it
because we want more quantity to
start the quality itself. So we
also as an organization, we also
pay, um, user journals, because
this is an open journal. This is
our pilot project. We call it up
letter, the pilot project
because we use open review. So
the reviewers and outers,
everything is open, the
reviewers can know this is not
blind review, because the author
knows who reviews their
manuscript. And reviewers also
participated voluntarily. We are
not bothered by the close rules
like subscribes or blind review,
or even dance for copyright.
Because this pub later is also
discuss about publication in
Indonesia. We also fund half a
fund funding for research in
academic publications in the
form to two groups of
researchers that research about
academic publication. So those
funding that we have, we share
it into it, our kit, and then
also with people who has ideas
to research in academic
publications. So the research
will be talking about
publications. Okay, this is my
last slide. Amano my last word
of the lifeless about Thank you.
We I call it never ending
learning because we encourage
also teachers to inform their
students, because we started to
look at to in the early age,
they can submit their manuscript
or their narrative science in
journal for school. This is also
our pilot projects. And I call
it never ending learning because
this is a very long route and
never ending because we always
update the informations the
system of the journal itself,
the changing rules in the
worldwide and the changing rules
in my governments. Sometimes
they're they're different in you
know, when they are deciding
what is good, what is bad. So
this Updating is doing all the
time. That's why the learning
process is always there. And the
off cycle one of them is also
the lack of Human Resources
along with language barriers, so
that we invite everyone here to
collaborate. If you want to
collaborate with us done. Don't
hesitate to drop an email for me
and celebrate this learning
process. Okay, that's all for my
presentation. In Indonesia, it
mediums in English, sharing to
enhance the publication's