Unknown: My name is Helena
Rasche, I've been working in
open source for quite some time
now I'm currently employed by
the hospice Medical Center and
the advanced folks who can
greater. And I'm here to tell
you a little bit about open
source in research. So first,
what is free and open source
software, the term is a bit
important. Because open source
software and free software are
not necessarily the same things
free software doesn't mean open.
So you can many of us remember
free were on the internet from
when we were younger. This is
software where you have no
access to source code and you
can't work with it, you can't
modify it due to license. This
is not great for science. On the
other hand, open source doesn't
mean free. So for those of you
who are producing research
software, just because you're
making your software open
source, it doesn't mean it has
to be free software. And this
together, the intersection of
these two is often known as free
and open source software, or
floss free slash library, open
source software. And this just
refers to off software there's
both open and free. Open source
is simply licensing your work so
it can be used how you want.
Making your software, open
source is just a matter of
setting out the terms of how you
want your software to be used,
it doesn't mean that you have to
give up control of your
software, it doesn't mean that
you're putting it out to the
community forever. It just means
you're choosing and saying for
yourself setting boundaries on
how you want your software to be
used. So it's very important
step all the time. For those who
want you open source also makes
it easy for others to remix your
software to reuse it to build
upon your software, add new
features if they want. And if
you're building a project where
community is important, where
you want your software to be
used by a lot of people, making
it open source in such a way
that people can reuse and work
with you can be a really great
boost for your software just in
terms of visibility and people
who want to use it, things like
that. So why use and promote
open source. Open source is part
of the ethics of scientists and
hackers a little bit when you're
writing the software when you're
working on projects together. A
lot of the libraries you use for
Python, things like this, if
you're using different
programming languages, a lot of
Python libraries you use will be
open source, you're benefiting
from a lot of work that other
people have done so far. And
it's a nice feeling to
collaborate and give back. Now
you've built your software or
your project on years and years
of free work that was produced
before and now you're giving
back to the community. It also
means distributed innovation. So
when you're making software open
source and free so that other
people can work on it. This
means that other people will
give back contributions, they'll
report bugs, when they have
issues running your software,
they will tell you new features
that they want. You don't have
to implement them. But you're
able to take all of these good
ideas from the community and
things like this. Importantly,
for science, open source is
easier to review, reuse and
integrate. And when we talk
about open source in science, if
you want your software to be
distributed widely to be used in
a lot of systems, one of the
best things you can do for it is
licensing it in such a way that
everyone can use it and set it
up on their own system. Things
like Aleksey so I'm of course
very biased here, and we'll talk
a lot about galaxy. But in the
galaxy community, we can give a
huge platform of you know,
unused galaxy, you 30,000 users
to free source, it's free
advertising. But we can only do
that for open source software.
There are a lot of risks
associated with closed code to
when you have closed source
software that's used in science,
you can't review it very easily,
the community can't review it
very easily only the reviewers
of the paper sometimes. And if
there are errors in the
software, if there are bugs,
then these can be missed for
years and years. And these
effects a lot of scientific
results downstream. So having
open source reviewable software,
it's very important for
reproducible, good quality
science. A lot of the journals
are adopting this and starting
to require disclosure or
publishing have your source code
for all of your software to this
is from a scientific
perspective, really a good thing
for the community. So how do you
know if something is open
source? You'll see on a lot of
GitHub repositories, which I
think everyone here is familiar
with, thanks to LS is a little
license icon on the right hand
side of the repository. Also on
things like slides, so you can
see the CC by of these, this
slide deck at the top, you can
look for a couple of different
files within the license. And
these files need to be there if
it's going to be open source
software that she can reuse. But
it's not just for software. I
know I talk a lot about software
but it's also for data. There
are different licenses for data
for things like databases that
you want to make accessible for
photos or training materials,
things like this. All these are
options. And if you want people
to be able to use them, you need
to license
them. One of common fears I hear
about a lot is, if I published
my software online, if I do it
in the open, it'll be I'll be
scooped someone will take my
software and claimants thrown.
But this isn't necessarily true.
If someone steals your software,
there is at least a traceable
log in GitHub, or which we'll
get to in a minute. There is a
copy of your software already
online. And if you already have
a community around that, it'll
be very obvious that someone
took it. And if you're still
worried, I've heard some people
saying that they publish
preprints as a way to document
that, hey, they were first write
the software, and to really make
sure they stake their claim on
that software. So don't worry
about that just work in the
open, it's better for the
community, it's better for the
world. And it's good for
science, publishing, sharing
open source code. One of the
easiest and most effective ways
to do this is version control.
I'm sure you're all learning
about getting GitHub if you
haven't already. But version
control is fantastic way to
publish and share code with
others. It gives you a whole
timeline of your software, and
it makes it easy to reuse,
contribute and make
modifications to your software.
So why collaborating is easy.
One of the common things is
reverting accidents. If you make
some bad changes in your code,
or one of your collaborators
does, you can always revert you
can always go back to before
then it makes it easy to
integrate the changes from
multiple developers. Like with
galaxy, there are some 200
contributors to the code base or
the training materials as well.
And all of us can work together
collaboratively because we use
version control. Also offsite
copies of your software,
everyone has computer issues,
everyone loses a hard drive at
some point or gets their
harddrive encrypted by some
hackers things like this. If you
have all of your work in the
open in public, then you can
just download a new copy again
and start working in Git and
GitHub are very common, a very
common choice. Git is one of the
most common version control
systems, there are others.
GitHub, likewise, is one of the
most common good hosts. But
there are others depends on what
you want to use. One of the nice
things you get with GitHub is a
large existing user base and
large community of people who
will be able to contribute to
your software to low barrier for
entry. If you need to learn more
about git, there is a great set
of lessons from software
carpentries. But one of the
important notes is that Git is
very, very complex. My partner
teaches a get together session
where they teach how to use Git
to the colleagues in our office.
And there is just so much to
learn about git, but you don't
need to learn all of it. Now.
Just start with the important
parts, the rest comes later.
There, you'll see a lot of
guides online that will say oh,
you need to learn about how the
commit craft works and things
like this. But if you just want
to publish your code, you don't
need any of the fancy stuff. So
a few steps to make your work
open source. It README is a very
important part of us. If you
want people to know what your
software is and how to start
using it. That's the number one
thing people will see. So be
sure to include lots of good
images there. License, if it
has, if it's going to be open
source, it needs a license file.
So it takes two minutes
satellite essence with GitHub,
it's really easy just doing same
thing tributing guide, GitHub
has some template contributing
guides that make it really easy
to tell people how you want them
to contribute to your to your
repositories. Having a public
roadmap, we aim to talk about
the Kanban boards and the agile.
Having a public roadmap is a
great way to tell community,
what you're working on what
features you're going to
implement things like that, that
can help people get excited for
your software. Publishing list
of issues same, it feels bad to
say, hey, my software has bugs.
But at least putting them out in
the open, you can track the
things you've done or not done.
A Code of Conduct assumptions
you've learned from MLS is very
important thing. Contact and
citation can be very useful as
well. If you have a GitHub
repository, you can easily get
those from Sunoco and figshare.
If you need to do I, there's a
nice website for how to choose a
license. There are lots of
different license choices. And
they give you a lot of different
freedom to choose what you want
your software to be able to do
or what you want other people to
be able to do with your
software. Some people don't want
businesses to use their software
for free. And there are licenses
that support this or some people
want everyone to use it for
free. Lots of different choices.
But the ultimate goal, of
course, is full reproducibility.
And we're getting a lot closer
with things like Jupiter and
binder where you can publish
your software but also a
notebook where people can run
your software online, which is a
fantastic way to get people to
use your software.
Taking it further. There's a lot
of ways for you to contribute if
you're a first time contributor
and to get involved in the open
Source Software movement and
contributing to the open source
communities. So there are lots
of nice links here if you want
to explore them. And lastly is
the Turing way has a nice
handbook on reproducible data
science and making software open
source and publishing and making
accessible to people. So with
that, thank you