David Selassie Opoku: My name is David
Selassie Opoku. I'm currently a
farmer, I saw somebody mentioned
that that was one of the goals.
So glad to see that. And also co
founder of green goat farms, and
also recently, fellow at the
Stanford digital civil society
lab, where exploring issues
around African food sovereignty.
So to start off, I want to start
with the definition of social
intrapreneurship. I pick this up
from Shopify actually has a
definition that I like, and it
says that it's doing business
for social cause. It might also
be referred to as altruistic
intrapreneurship. Interesting.
And then it combines commerce
and social issues in a way that
improves the lives of people
connected to a cause. And their
success usually is not measured
in profit alone. But then he
asked the question, should an
entrepreneurship be social, then
because everything should
benefit people. So I tend to
generally look at it as
intrapreneurship should be
social. Now, I mentioned this,
because I think there's a strong
connection to open science and
the principles that exist within
open science and openness. I
think the cheering way really
highlights some of these
aspects. If you've not checked
out a resource, you should check
it out. We share our weekend
team have mentioned this several
times. When we talk about
collaboration, we talk about
project design, we talk about
reproducibility, communication,
outreach, ethics, all these to
some extent, I lead into social
outcomes that benefit not just a
group of individuals, but
anybody, we're talking about
accessibility. I think anyone
who practices this, and sub
build enough skills, that ends
up being very relevant to social
enterpreneurship. So now I'm
going to talk about my journey.
And I hope through this, you'll
be able to see how what I ended
up doing to some extent, led me
to the path where I could feel a
little bit more comfortable or
adventures to be in a social
entrepreneur. So I'll start from
Ghana, I lived there for about
17 years of my life, lower
middle class, Christian family
farming family. And then I was
privileged to get a scholarship
to go to last two years of high
school in Costa Rica ended up
being in class with students
from over 65 different
countries, which started
exposing me to the world and
around commonalities that we had
and also differences. But I
think the heart of that became
that we are all very similar. We
all care about generally similar
issues. And, and that was a life
changing moment. I did six years
in the US where I did my
undergrad and my Master's in
biology, and then computer
science, and also did some
research with UNICEF, and a lot
of civic engagement work. And I
think in all of that, studying
to understand how what I was
learning was going to be helpful
to different individuals,
different communities, whatever
I did, should have an impact on
communities. I then returned to
Ghana, and worked at a tech
incubator. And one of the things
that I quickly became a champion
of because that really didn't
exist was the local Open Data
advocates. And the reason was
because at least in Ghana, at
that time, a lot of
intrapreneurs were trying to
build products, or trying to
work with data. But most of the
data sets were not
contextualized, to Ghana and
most of Africa. So I became the
person who was pushing this
forward, which then led me into
the open data space. I joined
Open Knowledge Foundation, which
is an organization that works in
promoting Open Data principles,
and was fortunate enough to
become the data what I call a
data plumber, helping
journalists, civil society
organizations, researchers think
about how open data principles
openness can be embedded into
the work that you do. At the
heart of that was really
recognizing that accessibility
in terms of solving issues was
was a big thing to pay attention
to. And I think in their became
the values that now have led me
to leaving to focus on building
a farm. And the reason why I
left become a farmer built green
gold farm was because I saw a
problem that across the world,
we have an issue around how
we're going to feed the world,
farmers are a very important
group of people who are going to
be leading this, but at the same
time, most of the time, they
don't have access to the skills
and the resources that we need
to push this forward. And so
greencoat is seeming to figure
out ways to do that with farmers
in resource constraints
environments.
And so I've talked about social
enterpreneurship. I've talked
about open science, and I think
at the heart of all of those,
our community. You hear that
being repeated in these two
spaces, you hear about the
comments where there's
collective ownership of some
kind of research. was very
successful. And then you hear
about society. And I think for
anyone who believes in these
principles who practices this,
who uses this social
entrepreneurship is also an
avenue for you to explore
because you are definitely
unexpressed, and some of the
challenges that you deal with or
you have mastered, will become
relevant there. Um, so a little
bit about going gold farms, we
have four main phases that we
want to go through, one to
consistently produce healthy and
affordable food, using
sustainable and accessible
practices want to build the
capacity of other smallholder
farmers to produce sustainably
and smallholder farmers because
we believe that they actually
build or have the ethos around
sustainability, food sovereignty
that is needed in this world.
And we want to make smallholder
farms and farmers more
resilience to processing of
their produce, and then finally
want to turn farms into spaces
of education, innovation,
urgency, and how that's a day or
week look like. In a day or in a
week I'm reading or my team and
I were reading about ways of
implementing research to this
problem. So everything from
reading about freedom plants in
and about GMO, and why that
leads to outcomes that actually
doesn't benefit communities, or
even looking at science and ways
to make data much more
accessible. or helping my dad
was a farmer for over 40 years,
but doesn't really collect it.
And the way that makes it much
easier for him to appreciate
that and make that much more
accessible to him. So putting
together and unable to team up
on the latest. So that's level
of collaboration, we can do
things alone. So how do we bring
in teams of different experts to
do this, and then believing in
ourselves each and every day? So
I just wanted to say so social
enterpreneurship Should I do it
there, there are four things
that I put down that may be
helpful if you want to consider
this, um, you see a social age
that no one you know, is
solving. Yeah. So that may be
one factor to consider another.
If there's no fixed salary, no
problem. That's, that's
something we can talk about
later. But it's not, the comfort
of having a salary in other
spaces may not always be
guaranteed. You tend to be a
generalist by nature, but
especially it's by necessity. So
you do everything, and then you
specialize in specific areas
that you want, when it's needed.
And if not, now, when there's
something that you've always
wanted to explore, and maybe
now's the time you try it out,
and you figure out whether this
is a path to pursue, or maybe it
was a waste of your time, at
least you know that. So these
are some things that you will
consider if you want to pursue
this path. And then I want to
wrap up with three anecdotes
that I've picked up that I
believe have helped me so far.
And even other people that
advice when proceeded
intrapreneurship path. So be
versatile. And I said generalize
and then specialize think
socially intrapreneurship
leverages on the ability to
generalize, being interested in
different things, different
issues, and how to solve that,
and then finding a way to
specialize in whatever that
issue is. And again, so for me
being able to understand data,
but being able to understand
product development, being able
to understand different
societies and cultures and the
way that they behave. And then
specializing on a specific
skills, I think social
intrapreneurship gives you the
ability to start off as a
generalist and then look at an
issue and where you want to
specialize in that. Um, I think
to do this, you need to see
people are the heart of this is
people that you're working with,
they're either dealing with
issues, or they're innovating,
and being able to start with
them as people before whatever
technology whatever solution is
important. But also letting
yourself be seen. As opposed to
either be in academia, or even
being in a lab. it being a
social entrepreneur, you need to
be out there, you need to be
talking to customers, you need
to be talking to communities
need to be building that
relationship, but you also have
to let people see you. Let them
know you for who you are.
And so that's important. And
that's one of the anecdotes that
I've picked over time. And then
this is kind of a joke, but Greg
is the identity in your job,
actually do not grant the
identity in your job, your job
will go, but who you are as a
person wouldn't. And I think
being able to find ways to
thrive outside your job, whether
it's as a social entrepreneur,
whether it's as somebody who is
in a company who is in a
university in a lab, letting
your identity not be grounded in
that because that could always
change is a valuable thing that
I've learned. In the past maybe
six months, there have been many
opportunities that I have feel
that I have not been accepted in
and learning and that that is
not what my identity is. My
identity is beyond that. It's
been something that keeps me
going. So without my last thing
that I'll say is that brief, the
most important thing, especially
in this time of COVID is your
life. Everything else is
replaceable. And I think if you
want to go down the path of a
social enterpreneur or any other
career option, just making sure
that you live in a life that is
balanced, that you can thrive
and be healthy as well. We'll
keep you going into whatever
path you take. So stay human,
and be open. And with that, I
will end here