Andre Maia Chagas: Without hardware
without equipment, there is no
science in a way, right? Like we
can download all these amazing
data sets. But if you really
want to be in control of
generating data and like doing
so exciting questions locally,
and questions that are important
for your science and your
community, let's say, then you
need the proper tools to do it,
right. Malik already introduced
me, but Hello from my side, so
that I get started. I work at
University of Sussex, where I
have a job that really that I
really, really like, which is
developing open source hardware.
For the Department of
neurosciences. I'm also
volunteering a lot of my time to
train in Africa, which is an
NGO, trying to help development
in higher education in Africa.
So we do a lot of sharing of our
knowledge so that people can
actually build their own tools,
we do a lot of workshops, I
started a small website called
Open neuroscience. And I'm
working with Alia terenzo, and
Alex kucera, as part of the
Convention on this program, that
it's similar to open Life
Sciences, but for hardware
called Open hardware makers. All
of this started about I mean, I
think already spoke about like,
why open hardware, right, like
we need hardware to do the
experiments, the things that we
do. And here's just one example
in life sciences, right. So if
you are thinking about
microscopes, which is one of the
workhorses inside Life Sciences,
right? These tools are from they
were first developed, like in
the late 1600s, I think, if I'm
not mistaken, and this one that
you see on the left is actually
from 19, the turn of the 20th
century. So 1904, or something,
and the one on the right is a
little bit more recent, as you
can see, like the modern
microscope didn't change much
over the last 100 years. And
still, if you want to get one on
the right, you would spend
something like 10,000 pounds,
right. And I mentioned costs,
because although we really like
to romanticize things about
science in the end, like we
still need to pay for things.
And so things things are really
expensive, although the
technology in them didn't change
much over the last 100 years,
right. So there is something
wrong there from my perspective.
But even if you don't consider
that, if you think about you
are, let's say in the global
software, I'm originally from
trying to buy a microscope, you
only find distributors from the
global norm. So you have to
import things, they only have
that, or they mostly have their
clients in the global north
mine. So if I bring it back to
my hometown, in Brazil, where it
was super hot, warm and humid,
then like the fingers gonna,
like rest really fast and
probably be out of work. If it
breaks, I have no local support,
I have no idea what's going on
inside because it's, it's a
black box. And as COVID-19 has
shown us, our supply chains, for
equipment for for a consumables
and all like they are really
fragile, right, like once like,
there is a disruption from like
China and so on, like, everybody
gets stalled, and things get
delayed, and so on. And so all
of this together makes
scientific equipment really slow
to innovate, right? Because you
cannot open like, I'm not gonna
fiddle around with a 10,000
pound piece of equipment, right?
Like, if I break it, like the
whole department is gonna want
my head. So like, I better not
fool around with that, right?
And so this is why like, without
access to these tools, proper
access, there is no science,
right? And this is where open
source comes in. This is just a
few examples of open source
microscopes. They're available
today, if you want to find these
projects online, right, you
could find and reproduce them
right away. And the nice thing
about them is that
all of them are under $100.
Right? Some maybe Actually,
let's say all of them were under
$200, which is like orders of
magnitude cheaper than the ones
that I just showed you. And
they're all portable. Right. So
here on the left, you have the
scale view, which is about five
centimeters. This is something
we developed in the lab A long
time ago. And we're using for
educational purposes and so on.
But you could do like 80% of the
stuff that you do in the labs,
right? This one next week is
actually very specialized for
fluorescence, which is like a
fancy method, right, like in
life sciences. But the one that
I would like to highlight or
this one, like the one left with
the yellow one, which is called
open fracture, which is an
amazing project that I really
like I'm not involved with the
project myself, but I really
like like the project because
they're actually made the papers
and prove that this actually is
able to detect malaria inside
blood cells. So the resolution
of this is on par with optical
microscopes. And you can build
it for a fraction of the cost
and 3d print parts wherever you
are actually. A lot of the
developers for design doesn't
year our partner developers with
the people here in Bath which is
close by To brighten Ram. And
the other microscope on the
right is actually about this big
and goes on the head of mice,
and they can actually do live
imaging of brain activity while
the animals are performing a
certain task. And what I think
is really crucial about these
two examples, these last two
that I said is that the yellow
one open fracture, they actually
showed that they can do better
like the same or better
performance than actual
commercially available
microscopes. And the one on the
right, is actually providing,
which is the miniscope project
can actually provide something
that wasn't available before. So
before the miniscope, is an open
project came along, there was no
way to have freely moving mice
and record their like brain
activity with optical imaging.
Right. And so, this brings a lot
of innovation, there is a big
community around miniscope, just
to like, pound on the point that
the speakers that came before me
said that fostering a community
and bringing people into an open
project actually is good for
research is good for you. And
it's good for innovation and
like speeding up the cycles and
science and research. So I
wanted to keep this kind of
short. So this is just a slide
that hooli made. And I adapted
to show why we should use open
hardware. And I hope I have
mentioned this already, even if
like too fast, and giving you a
lot of information. But let's
like take again, step by step.
So because it's reproducible. So
we actually use GitHub and
GitHub a lot to put out our
projects, our open hardware
projects, because it's actually
super fun to learn how somebody
did something like how the
miniscope, this amazing project
works, right, I can go into the
documentation, and actually see
how they put the boards
together, how the electronics
work, and so on. It's super
affordable. So from our
experience with people that are
being part of our workshops in
Africa, they say, look, this is
affordable enough that here in
our institution, we can like
pull some resources together and
get started with open source
hardware. It's repairable
because I know like everything
that is going on. Inside the
hardware, I can also know how to
repair it when something goes
wrong. But not even that,
because I know how everything
works. I also know if the data
that I get out of it is reliable
or not. Right? Like, Oh, is this
PCR? Or is this image from this
microscope Really? Well, it's
supposed to be or is it an
artifact? Right? Because I know
how it works, then I know the
limitations and the
capabilities. And because I know
the limitations and
capabilities, I know where and
how, and if I need to customize
something, right? So let's say
I'm using the open flexor for
something, but right now it
works on power in the in the
wall socket, right. But I needed
with batteries, because I know
like how it works, I can easily
say okay, if I change this power
supply with this batteries, then
I can actually bring this to the
fields and use it outside the
lab space or even in a lab where
there are constant power
failures, right? And putting all
of this together This is then
obviously, hopefully, if it's
done, right, it's democratizing,
right? Because then it doesn't
matter if you are in the global
north, or if you're doing
citizen science, or if you are
inside academia, because you're
collecting data with those that
you actually know exactly what
they're doing. You can go and
say, Look, this is my data. This
was how was recorded. And it's,
it's, it's good data, right? So
we need to discuss data and not
whether or not like I have a
$10,000 piece of microscope.
Luckily for us, there is what
I'm calling, like the Cambrian
explosion of open source
hardware going on. So what
you're seeing here are a lot of
projects that are currently
available. some highlights that
I think are really cool, like
here on the top left, you can
see this little object on the on
the palm of our hand, this is an
atomic force microscope. Right?
So this goes down to image like
really, really, really tiny
stuff. Right? So it really
measures like nanometers and
things that are really small.
Then here, on the bottom row,
you can see the the image where
there is somebody holding a
little whiteboard, this is
actually an EKG machine. And
this person actually discovered
that, like he writes a blog
post, and I can find the
reference later if somebody
wants. But he actually finds
that he has a heart arrhythmia,
because he was able to play
around with this EKG and brought
it to his doctor and said, Look,
this is my data. This is how my
heart looks like over a 2424
hour period. And there is
something wrong here. Let's fix
it right. And it could have been
that he would never like know
about this. But I think it's
interesting that people have the
empowerment to like know what's
going on with them. But on this
note, there is also a project
that is called Open insulin
where people are actually making
easily monitors and trying to
make their own insulin because
like price surges of insulin in
the us right now. For instance,
like crazy, and a lot of people
are really having bad times
managing to get their hands on
the proper insulin that they
need, and so on. And so this
also empowers people to say, you
know what, like, we are not
going to take this nonsense
anymore. And we're going to do
it our own way. And there are
many, many other projects,
right, just a little bit of data
on something that we're working
on at the moment, which is, this
is something that we're working
with just to show you that what
we're seeing here is the number
like the fraction of papers, as
a percentage of total
publications from government,
over time, from the 1990s to
2020, of papers that had either
open source hardware, open
hardware, or open lab were in
their abstract title, or
keywords. Right, so you can see
that this is not growing. I
mean, it's still a tiny, tiny
fraction of the total number of
papers, of course, but what I
like here is how fast new new
papers are coming more and more
each year. If people are
interested in this, I would
really recommend taking a look
at the gorge community, which is
the global Open Science hardware
community, which is mainly where
hooli, Alex and I met. But the
point that I'd like to make here
is that this is a really, really
global online community, most of
the time, where people really
from all continents are
discussing open hardware,
they're really, really open to
newcomers and really willing to
help with questions. And there
is I think, the most important
document that was done
collectively, as you can see on
the photo, on the bottom, right,
like this was the voting for
things in the manifesto that we
wrote, is like, what is the
point of the global open science
community and what is our
Manifesto, right. And you can
see the points highlighted here.
And this tries to make sure that
this is, is instill keeps going
as a really diverse and
horizontal community where
things are being discussed, and
all of these different
communities are being taken in
consideration. Again, I can
share the link for this, if I
did notice, here I have a slide
in the end with useful links,
this might be there. A little
bit of a shameless advert, I'm
sorry, so we are actually
finishing the curriculum for a
new program. And you can pre
register. So if you go to open
hardware dot space. And you can
also find more information about
this. And the idea of this
program is to take people that
are newcomers into open hardware
and to show them best practices,
right. So you're going to cover
a lot of things that are quite
similar in terms of like, Oh,
this is GitHub, or this is
Instructables. And these are all
these platforms. But also like
we're going to show like points
on documentation and licenses
and things because hardware,
believe it or not, most of
hardware projects need at least
three different licenses, which
is different from all the
projects that we've been
discussing right now. But yeah,
so I just wanted to say, please
take a look at the website, get
in touch, if you want, like will
be super, super happy to get
projects, or even just questions
from you. Because we are in the
moment where we're finalizing
our curriculum, and we're ready
to launch hopefully, in another
couple of months, and then still
run a cohort this year. With
that, I would like to say
thanks, you can ask me
questions. I think you're
writing hopefully, in the
document. You can find me on
Twitter, you can send me an
email as well. I'll be super
happy to chat. And just to say
that here's a list of what I
think are useful links