Unknown: My name is Joe Mambo,
I'm from Cameroon. And my
background is in biochemistry,
specifically molecular biology.
So, I got a bachelor degree on
molecular biology. And then I, I
studied science of education.
And I get, I got my two masters
degrees in science of education.
Then I did my PhD in, in public
communication at the university
level in Canada. So during all
my academic courses, I was
always, always 10 plays by
information, how information can
be shared how information can be
reused. And that is why from
this end place, I quoted the
open source movement eight years
ago with fraud ocsd, net open
and collaborative shells,
networks. And from OCS is net
founded our project, our project
was Project Server project to
promote Open Sans in French, and
in French speaking, African
countries and 80. So that is how
I wind my network crew
organization working in on open
access, open at wi n, any kind
of openness, open, or any kind
of dimension related to open
science. And luckily, I read so
many sketches like the
decolonial library, renewal and
the world. Today, I will spend
more time on the one with the
maker movement. But I want also
to turn that around shesha. I'm
doing research action, because
I'm also the neck lecturer at
the advanced School of mass
communication here in Cameroon
where I'm teaching digital
humanities, open science and all
what is related to scholarly
communication. So that is, that
is me. So don't worry. I found
that the one in 2018 and is a
kind of reification of my thesis
because my thesis is on the
maker movement and the technical
reality in French African
countries. So, the Mwana is a
kind of concrete realization of
what I learned from the one app
and the one app is specialized
on biotechnology due to my
background in in biochemistry.
So, what we are doing the one
that we have like related to
public health and biotechnology,
you have three main activity,
can you hear me Yeah. Thank you.
So, we have like three men
activity related to public
health. So, the first one is a
very complex one local
production of enzyme reagents.
So that is a high level of of
molecular biology if I can say
and what we are doing, we are
put here seeing as I'm looking
at it because when I stopped my
studying biochemistry 16 years
ago, it was mostly because I was
impressed by molecular biology,
but they told us that we cannot
do it from Cameroon from now
because equipment operation as
so expensive. So, when I are
going to open says moving
movement, I realized that true
openness, there is a lot of
things that I can overcome a lot
of barriers of place and in my
past that I can overcome and
help a new generation generation
of African and Cameroonian to,
to succeed in molecular biology.
So we are producing an enzyme
for Molecular Biology and
currently we are so we are
sending the those anzai in
Cameroon I in India That way we
have some collaborators of every
way in Santander, Africa when
someone need answered. So, that
is like the deep molecular
biology part of our work we are
doing in the Adam one lab. And
the second thing is local
hardware manufacturing, because
one thing that advocating for is
local manufacturing, because we
need in terms of openness, we
don't need to work with black
box, we need to be able to fix
all equipment, if they are
broken, and we need to
understand the process from the
beginning to the end, how such
equipment will so that is why
also we are working with some of
equipment used by ourselves. And
some of my work related to this
has been featured in through
natural articles talking about
all the work we are doing at one
of our third activities,
capacity building, because it's
very important for us to build a
new generation of Cameroonian
and, and African able to
understand to trust, able to
trust in themselves and able to
build things from Africa from
what we are doing. So we are
teaching we used to we are
working with local university.
So used to post Intel we need we
used to train them through a
workshop. And but it's not easy,
because we have some challenges
and founding foundings the first
one because we are defending of
international collaboration
sometime. And the there is a
kind of lack of lack of local
awareness and support. So we are
trying to overcome all this kind
of barrier. And also very
important is some barriers, like
language barriers, I'm sure that
you understood that I'm not
English is not my primary
language that I have. French is
my I have I don't own my studies
or my school in French. So
French, if I can see even if the
two language colonial language
for us, but French is I'm free
and influential on learning
English, so that sometimes also
it can be a barrier for for us.
And we we don't have the the
government support also. So it's
very important to have the
government support but here is
very difficult, but through the
good vibes we have and the good
collaboration, we have an
international level we are still
sustainable through the research
development we are doing. And
yes, this just to say, thank
you. This is a small team, the
small team of them one if some
woman be here, that is the
permanent, the permanent and
one. And we have a lot of
volunteer and intern but here is
the five permanent often when
I'm doing all the magics and the
work. So thank you very much for
your attention.