Lenny Teytelman: I often start with one
of my favorite tweets from a
postdoc at UC Riverside Who says
I'm looking, reading a paper,
looking for a protocol in 1997.
Paper, as described the 96 finds
96 paper as described an 87,
find 87 paper, it paywalled. And
that's a very common and
frustrating experience. This is
from a biologist, here's one
from a physicist, where he says
devices were fabricated, as
previously described, previously
described, previously described
and the original reference as
devices were fabricated with
conventional methods, right? So
good luck, while reading the
paper and figuring out exactly
what was done and how to
replicate it and building it.
And this is really the mission
of protocols that I owe is to
improve what we publish to make
it easier to share our methods
long before publishing and
preprint or semi privately. And
then after you publish that, as
I said, with my own personal
experience, to have a place
where we can come back to, to
share corrections and
optimizations. I've shared the
slides. So I don't want to do
much with the slides, I just
want because this is really
quick to show a little bit of
the platform and what I think
makes it unique. So our mission,
as I said, is to make this
sharing easier and more rigorous
protocols that IO is open access
CC by license for everything
that's public, if you're sharing
our business model is we charge
for keeping things private,
private collaborations, if
you're an industry and you're
never publishing, that's paid,
if you're sharing publicly, just
as bio archive is free to read,
free to share open access CC by.
And,
you know, as I said, we started
in 2014. We're now at a point
where we have over 9000 public
protocols. And here's one of my
favorite examples. These are not
just PDFs, they're dynamic, and
interactive. People add videos
inside to show you what exactly
they mean grind the tissue, you
can show the 10 second video, we
have catalogs from reagent
vendors, so you can detail
exactly what do you use? What
are the materials that are
needed, where you've ordered
that. And one of my favorite
examples, is this protocol from
a researcher in Australia
National University. And if you
look at this step in the
protocol, doesn't matter what
the details are. But this step,
think of it as a recipe for
cooking. This step says, do
something for two to two minutes
timer, and it says seven
minutes. And this is confusing.
And instead of an email
exchange, or this being a final
paper, because protocols are
dynamic and interactive, you can
mouse over on the step, you can
click on it, you can ask a
question. And you can see on the
right hand side, one of the
researchers reading it said wait
to be two to seven minutes. What
does that mean? The question
goes to the author and everyone
who's using the protocol. And
you can see the reply right
there. So instead of private
email conversations and
answering a question the same
question 10 times to different
people, you sort of have a
public FAQ, that being built up.
And with a click of a button,
you can create a new version.
Again, going back to the first
talk we heard today, you can
create a new version, that
conversation is still there. But
this gets its own dry, you can
cite specific versions. And now
you can see it says that step is
fixed. There was a typo. The
author made version four and it
says whoops, right, that should
be two to three minutes timer is
not seven anymore. So it's
corrected. And if you go next to
the title, there is a compare
button that allows you to see
what is the same, what's
different between the steps,
what was modified between the
versions, right? So you have a
snapshot and a bird's eye view
of what are those differences?
What are the tweaks and
optimizations? Now, obviously, I
cannot change your protocol. I
cannot create a new version of
it only the author, the owner of
the protocol can. But we do have
just as on GitHub, we do have
copying and forking, so I can
make a branch of your protocol.
You work with grasshoppers, I
work with crickets, you're doing
this step at room temperature, I
do it at 30 degrees. And so I
can make a clone of your
protocol it becomes mine. I can
edit it as I use it with my
equipment with my strainer
species. And then when I'm
ready, I can share it and we try
it Give really clear credit to
both the original authors and to
show what's the evolution of the
protocol. So you can see on this
protocol itself, you can see
that it is a fork from another
protocol. And you can look at
that history, you can click on
the forks tab to see what's the
evolution of the versions and
forks and the same compare and
contrast functionality that
applies. There are a lot of it's
a we have a really powerful
editor that is kind of like
Microsoft Word or Google Docs,
concurrent editing, but really
meant for methods with regions,
which which data set did you
use, right catalog numbers,
videos, all of the things that I
mentioning. So check it out. It
doesn't cost anything to create
an account start sharing
protocols, as I said, is free.
You can always get in touch
requests in one on one demo. For
more in depth, I don't have time
to talk about everything we've
built since 2014. But for open
science, specifically, I did
want to highlight some things.
So we have communities. It's not
just a giant repository. We have
9000 public protocols at this
point that's growing quickly.
But we also let people create
communities where you can
organize the methods together.
So this is this is a one year
old, obviously, community of
people who are working on
Coronavirus related methods.
There's half 1000. Researchers
in this group 230 plus protocols
for sequencing testing for
wastewater monitoring, tracking
variants. And because these are
communities when new protocols
come in, or when updates happen,
everyone is notified. Everyone
knows when there's a new
version, a new fork a new
protocol added or when
discussions happen that I showed
you. So it becomes a
collaborative method development
workspace that's out in the
open. You can also have private
side but I really wanted to
focus on the mission and the
public side of this. And from
these Coronavirus protocols I
really want to highlight because
it's just an amazing example I
want to highlight this protocol
from it's actually funded by
Wellcome Trust, the group that
shared it from University of
Birmingham. This was the first
protocol on Coronavirus that we
got on protocols that I owe
January 25th of 2020. And what I
find amazing about it is that
the group that shared it, you
can see it's actually a fork
from there. This is a sequencing
of the Coronavirus RNA. This
protocol is a fork from what
they shared in September of
2019. Before we even had
Coronavirus. It's a fork from
their Ebola protocol. And they
share the same 100 plus methods.
This is funded by Wellcome Trust
and UK, ri. Their work they
shared this Ebola protocol in
September. And as soon as they
got the SARS, cov to sequencing
going in January, with a click
of a button they made a fork,
they changed those few things.
And again, you can do the
Compare and contrast. And you
can see what was in the Ebola
protocol. And it's tiny things
right. As you can see, when you
click compare, the differences
are really small. Let me
actually go back to the first
version, it's easier to
demonstrate. So what they share
on January 22. I said 25th it
was January 22. If you click the
Compare to check it against the
bolo protocol, the differences
are really tiny. They use the
same amount of dntps random
hexamers. And you know step two
is the same step one, instead of
10 microliters of Ebola RNA, you
need 11 microliters of SARS cov.
To write it's a small
difference, but it's important.
And this is really critical for
methods that microliter can make
big difference for efficiency.
It's the same as my story with
that one microliter to five
microliters making or breaking
the protocol. And this is a
beautiful example because they
were able to share it quickly.
They were already on the
platform. They had the bullet
protocol out they shared it
rapidly in a year. If you look
at this protocol, right? No,
it's not a paper. But there are
120,000 views of it. There are
2000 export into PDF printing it
out right 57 people made copies
of it and modified it as they
use it in their research group
to get the whole genome
sequencing source code 260
comments of it.
And no it's not a paper. We're
not a journal. It makes end up
in a paper at some point. But
this is that rapid sharing
preprint like sharing that is
critical to open science. And
before I take questions, the
last thing that is really
special for me in highlighting
is when you're not just sharing
a supplementary, but you're
putting things in the right
repository, same way that we put
protein sequences and PDB. And
DNA sequences in GenBank. When
you put things in the right
repository, they become
discoverable. And I showed the
live demo so I Gibbs skip those
slides. And I love this example
where a researcher in Chile is
asking does anybody have a
protocol for RNA extraction from
primary cortical neuron
cultures, a postdoc at UCSF says
there's a couple on protocols
that I owe, but here's the one
that I recommend for you. And
what is what feels so amazing to
me about this example is that
when you look at the protocol
itself, that the postdoc pointed
to that should work for this
Chilean scientists. The protocol
accompanies a paper in the
journal Giga science on
parasites of stickleback fish,
right. So it has nothing to do
with cortical neuron cultures,
that paper is parasites or
stickleback fish. But because
they didn't just add a PDF as a
supplementary file to their
paper and chances that
somebody's looking for protocol
for cortical neuron cultures
would be reading this paper,
close to zero, but because the
author's shared it openly in a
repository, not only did they
make their paper more rigorous
and reproducible and easier for
others to repeat, but they're
adding to the knowledge base
where people can find their
protocol for good use it for
their technique, use it for
their species with their
equipment. And so I will end
there, there are a lot of
funders that are now
recommending protocols that I
owe over 500 journals. When you
submit a paper, I encourage you
to put a protocol protocols that
are yo and link to it. So take a
look at the platform. And I'll
stop there and would be
delighted to answer questions.
Boy, and the most. I'm rushing
so much to make sure that
there's time for questions that
the most important slide I
didn't put up. This is the team.
I get the credit for the work I
didn't do I didn't program the
apps. I didn't build the
platform. That's my These are my
brilliant co founders Alexia and
Irina from day one of protocols
that I owe Alexei has been
leading the engineering team,
and we welcome feedback requests
suggestions, and we're working
daily. Even though we launched
back in 2014. We're working
daily on making it better and
making it work for researchers
like you