Yo Yehudi: I'm going to talk a bit
about one tool that we like to
use at the very start of the
open life science cohorts, which
is the open canvas. And so if
I'm on the right window, I'm
going to talk about it. Now,
we're going to ask you to follow
up after the call, because it
takes a little while to spend
some time thinking about it. But
we'll walk through what it is
and why it might be useful, just
right now. So just going back
also to the Mozilla's open
leadership framework, this is
just to remind us, we're
focusing really specifically on
the design elements. If you
recall Malvika was talking
about how important it is to
design conscious pathways for
people to contribute and to be
involved in your open science
and community projects. So here,
we're looking really
specifically at what we can do
to design these pathways. And
this rubric, again, is something
we'll see quite often as we're
working through, ols. And so
this time, we're talking about
ways that we can find our
projects to empower
understanding, sharing, and
participation and inclusion
really specifically, I'm not
going to focus too much time on
this. But it is really
interesting to look through the
open leadership framework when
you have a minute or two. So
this is the open canvas and you
say, Oh, no, it's a form filling
exercise. It is. But it's really
useful one because it really
helps you to reflect on what
you're doing and where you're
going and why. So we're going to
actually drill in what each of
these little boxes means and why
they're useful. So we have some
sort of examples here. So you
can refer back to these slides.
And it sort of gives you some
hints about how you might want
to fill it out. But I'm going to
skip forward a little bit and
just talk about each of the
boxes individually, and why we
care and why we think they're
useful. So first of all, we've
divided this into two halves.
One is on the left, there's the
product. And on the right there
is the community. So one is
really about the thing that
you're offering. And the other
side, we're talking more about
the people who you're involving,
when you're doing this, because
it's never really just about the
project that you're working on.
It's also always about the
people that you're working with
as much as anything. So digging
into box number one, the
problem. So just, if you can
print this out, print it if
otherwise, bring it up on Google
Slides or fill this out on your
computer, but try and write down
when you're doing your project,
what is the problem that you're
trying to solve? So for ols, for
example, the problem that we are
trying to solve might be that
open science is not something
that is well known. And it's not
something that's easy. You can't
just bring it fully formed  and not know
how to show share your work in
an effective way. And then if we
move on to the next thing, what
is then your proposed solution?
So you know, you know you have a
problem? How would you like to
fix it? In our case, this was
run a 16 week mentorship program
to help people learn a bit more
and spread the word to others as
well. And then, how will you
know that what you're doing is
something that is successful. So
what are your key metrics for
this? So once again, for lls
this might be and doesn't have
to be one example could be OLS is
the number of people who have
participated in the program. So
in OLS2, we had about 20
projects, and in our OLS3,
we have almost 40 projects and
over 60 participants. So this is
a metric that shows us that we
are in fact being successful and
spreading the word. And then now
that you've got an idea of what
you want to do, and how you want
to measure it, the next question
is what resources do you need to
build this and this could be I
need somewhere to put a website,
it could be I need people that
are you know, I need their brain
power. Or maybe I need a coder,
maybe I need someone who's a
community manager to help me
out. Or maybe I want a designer,
there are so many different
things that you might need. And
it really depends on your
project. But just try and think
if you want to get the basics,
just the real kickoff, what what
resources do you need to
assemble to get there. And now
we actually move on to the
community side where we start
thinking more about those people
because one of those resources
may in fact, be the people. And
so if you had someone who's
contributing to your project,
think about who they are and
what they might look like. So
again, if I'm thinking about
OLS, for example, then some
of our contributions might be
open science practitioners who
are our mentors and our experts,
and they can actually give
advice to other people. I'm
going to skip this box and move
on to user profiles. So the
target audience so who do we
want to be using this? So if
you're thinking about your
project, and this is something
that you're building so that
other people can use it and
participate that's slightly
different from contributors,
because contributors are the
people who help you build this
users of people actually use
what you've built. And so for
OLS, the user profile would be
many of you who are here
participating as the project
leads and the mentees. And then
you start thinking a bit about
the channels. So now that we
know who the people we want to
work with are we say, Well, how
can we gain them? So for
example, for us to get
contributors for OLS, a lot
of the time our channel was
simply email, we used our
personal networks, and we said,
Hey, lovely person who we think
you can be a mentor, can you
participate? Another one might
be Twitter, for example, if you
share on social media, there may
be other ways depending on what
your community is, it might be
that you're reaching out to
someone local to you, or a
research network or something
else like that. But that was
previously for contributed
channels. This is again, the
these are the people who are
helping you build what you
build. And now we're thinking
how can what channels do we use
if we want to find people who
want to learn from what we
build, who want to participate,
but not necessarily as a
contribution. So gaining new
users, for OLS, I think a lot
of us has been word of mouth,
for example. But also people who
have participated have been
shared it within their networks.
And we've done things like
podcasts, and we've done talks,
and we've done blog posts, and
we've done social media to try
and gain the new users as the
new project leads and the new
mentees. So have a think about
what your user channels are and
how you'd get gain new users.
And this is the community
engagement sort of subset of
boxes. And finally, now that
you've thought about all of
these things, think, what is the
clear message to state what you
offer? What Why do people wants
to come to you what what is the
catch the exciting thing, and
this might be perhaps, restating
your problem and solution, but
in a short and concise sentence,
and also just explaining why
you're different to others. So I
tried to think what this will be
for OLS. Probably something
about the fact that we are
experienced Open Science
practitioners who have been
working with community for
collaboratively for quite a long
time. And that we are able to
teach this and passes on to
other people. But again, try and
think about what this might mean
for your project as well. And so
here is an example of one that's
been filled out with a project
in mind where people will get
badges for working on open
science. So it gives you a bit
more of an idea about what it
might look tangibly with when
it's been applied to a project.
Again, this the link to the
slides is available on the notes
documents, you can go back to
this and you can view it
yourself in your own time. And
we also have a link so that you
can write your own open canvas
and I think this is one of our
assignments for the week, which
is so it's bit dot L y slash o
LS dash open dash canvas.