Esther Plomp: My name is Esther
Plomp. I'm a data steward at the
Delft University of Technology
in the Netherlands. And I'm also
one of the mentors of this
cohort. And you can find the
link of this presentation in the
slide itself. And I should have
also pasted the link in the
notes. So do let me know if you
cannot access it. So open data.
What is open data? Open Data is
any data that's made freely
available for use and reuse by
anyone and everyone. So what
does that mean? It means that
everyone should have access to
the data. So it should be
available on the internet, for
anyone to access on demand.
Everyone must be able to use
reuse and redistribute that
data. So participation is also
very important here. It should
also be transparent what kind of
information or what kind of open
data you're accessing. So there
should be some information about
data generation, and collection
and about the data. In terms of
reuse and distribution, that's
very important for open data,
you should be able to
redistribute data without a lot
of restrictions. And we'll get
back to that later. And open
data should also be
interoperable. And that means
that you can integrate it or
link it to other data. And if
you do that, in a machine
readable format, it's easy to do
that automatically. So these
definitions are from the Open
Data handbook and the World
Bank, and I pasted those things
in the slides. So do have a look
at those websites. If you want
to learn more about the
terminology. What is open data
and not or? Yeah, just to
highlight that the sentence data
will be available upon request
is not a good sign in terms of
open data. So I'm sure we've all
seen this sentence in a
publication where the author
states that sure if you email
me, or if you call me, I will
provide you the data. So it does
not open because you can't
actually access it by yourself,
you would have to go through the
author. And a study by vines and
colleagues has indicated that is
not as easy as it sounds, you
can email researchers. But
because we tend to hop
institutes, we change our email
addresses quite frequently. So a
lot of the time, it's going to
be difficult to contact a
researcher. So their conclusion
in their paper was then also
that research data cannot be
reliably preserved by individual
researchers, which might sound a
bit harsh. But to be fair, I
don't think we should be asking
individual researchers to
preserve data for the long term.
That's why we have data
repositories. What is also not
open data is fair data. So this
is a term that's been used
increasingly in the data world.
But it's actually not the same
as having data that is open. So
fair, means findable,
accessible, interoperable and
reusable. And what does that
practically mean? I put some
links into the slide, where you
can look it up in detail. But
I'm going to do it very briefly
right now. So finable means that
your data is finable on a data
repository with some metadata,
so information about the data,
and a persistent identifier. And
this persistent identifier
ensures that you do not end up
with a broken link. So that
means that your data is going to
be accessible as well. So
accessible, is seems kind of
like it's open. But that's not
actually what's accessible in
the word fair is about
accessible means that there's a
procedure in place that allows
you to obtain access to the
data, potentially, but your X's
can still be declined, but there
should be a procedure in place.
So this is where it's different
from open data is not
necessarily open. It can be but
not necessarily. But here also
we see that interoperable plays
an important part of fair and
your data is interoperable when
you use open formats, so formats
that anyone can use such as PDF.
Instead of Word documents, for
example, not everyone has a word
license and can just use that
software. But also, if you use
commonly use vocabulary or
standards to describe your data,
that means it's more easy to
integrate it with other data and
more easily understandable for
others. Same goes for reusable.
If you want your data to be
reusable, you should document it
well, so that others can
interpret the data. And in order
to do that it has already been
mentioned for software. But the
same goes for data, you can set
up a readme file, and I put put
two examples of README files in
the presentation. So do please
have a look if you want an
example. And also, there are
things such as data
dictionaries, or code books,
there's a little bit more
elaborate in comparison to the
readme file. But it's also very
good practice to document your
data so that others can actually
reuse it. And then, what is also
the same for data as for code,
in order for it to be reusable,
you need a license. And for
data, the most commonly used
licenses are the Creative
Commons licenses. So we do use
different licenses than
software. Because data and
software are different objects,
it functions a little bit
different. So I would not
recommend using the Creative
Commons license for software.
But for data, this is standard
practice. And the licensed use
of our software was already
linked before this, I'm actually
linking to the same one, because
it's a very nice website. But
for data, we now also have a
licensed user. So you can go to
the link in the slides to check
that out. So just briefly, also
introduced whether licenses is
basically a sort of standardized
contracts, that tells anyone
what they can do with your data.
So they don't have to ask you
what you allow them to do with
it. And as actually why it's
very important to have this
license out there in the open.
Because if your data or your
software doesn't have a license,
it means no one can actually use
it without asking you. So this
is why it's very important to
have that license. I'm getting
distracted by I'm not looking at
that right now. Sorry, we'll get
through it later, hopefully.
Right, open data has cc zero or
CC by licenses. This means that
there is no law of restrictions
for every user of your data. So
for example, cc zero or the
public domain allows the user to
do basically anything with your
data. And they don't even have
to attribute you. So they don't
necessarily have to cite you.
Does good practice, though. So I
would recommend the Cite your
sources. But if you would like
to enforce that a bit more, you
could use the CC by license. So
that allows the same things as
you can see in the slides as the
public domain. But it also
ensures that every year should,
should cite you or credit you.
And then the further down you go
with these licenses, you see
that they get a little bit more
restrictive. So for example, the
CC by non commercial non
derivative, the one at the very
bottom of this list, that one
does allows you to copy and
publish the data, but it doesn't
allow for commercial use, and
you can't actually modify and
adapt it. So this is not really
open data in a sense, because
there's a lot of restrictions
that are placed on the data. But
in any case, if you want to
choose that licensed that is of
course, up to you. And also just
a highlight here. If you're not
sure what license to choose for
your project and you want to
share data, please also feel
free to contact me if you just
want to ask or just have a chat
about it. And then something
which I find very important is
that it's not just about the
access to the data and
redistributing the data.
So I pasted two of my favorite
quotes regarding Open Science on
the slide, which is that there
is no Open Science if science is
not open to all. And that's a
quote from the blog post. Bro
open science is broken science
and can recommend to read that
one. And also the quotes
including more ways of knowing
and understanding our common
World Within the great
scientific conversation would
enrich and diversify its
collective ideas and creativity
for the common good. And that
quote is from open science
beyond open access, and that's a
report which I also highly
recommend that you read. So it's
really not just about having
access to things. I think open
data is really about anyone
allowing to participate in the
creation and generation of the
data as well, because otherwise,
I don't think it's truly open.
And if you want to learn more
about that, there's the data
equity framework by we'll count.
And there is a webinar on data
justice talk story, which I
recommend and a book on data
feminism by Catherine de Ignacio
and Lau and clay. So they go a
little bit more into the topic
on why it's important that
everyone can participate. And
then I also listed some
additional resources. bola
Anthony Martinez gave a similar
presentation to this one last
year for core two, and it's a
really good presentation. So do
have a look. And if you want to
really participate in open data,
and you want to get more
involved, I can recommend
joining the research data
Alliance, which is a global
research community that really
wants to increase awareness and
facilitate sharing of data. So
this is a great way to get in
touch with colleagues, and get
involved to initiatives and
working groups and do some
really practical stuff, as well
in terms of data sharing, of
course, during way, already been
highlighted. But it has an open
research or reproducible
research chapter. So you can
also find more information
there. And the open data, open
data Handbook, by the Open
Knowledge Foundation. And then
if you you're running out of
time, and you don't want to read
full data, books, and
presentations and all these
things, I listed two blocks 10
arguments against open science
that you can win by morphicon.
And I'm not necessarily saying
that you need to be an open data
evangelist. But if you're
hesitant about sharing your
data, this is also a good blog
to read, and maybe reconsider
why you're hesitant about this.
And I also wrote a short blog
about how can you make research
data accessible so I'm
shamelessly plugging that. And
this blog is a bit more
practical in terms of how you
can actually make your data
open. So we can't really go into
that right now because time
restrictions