Georgia Aitkenhead: I'm here to talk about
participator in citizen science,
which are two very closely
related scientific methods that
are very valuable wind, and I
think also quite productive
towards open research and open
science. And I'm here with some
citizen scientists who are
working with me on the project,
Suzanne, who I owe to Smith and
Sarah Markham, they're all
fantastic contributors, they're
autistic. And they're going to
talk to you in more detail about
their experiences and areas of
expertise. So just to go through
some very brief explanations.
Citizen Science basically
involves any science and which
people who are non professional
scientists take part. Many of
you may be familiar with
zooniverse, or open source
funding. These are ones that
target very particular parts of
the research cycle.
participatory science is in many
respects a more stringent
requirement. It means that the
people for whom there is most at
stake in the research are
involved in empowered positions
and directing directions,
setting positions. So not just
consultants, and not just doing
some part of the process without
knowing why they have to be
informed and they have to be
able to direct it. I think this
is really important for breaking
down the boundary between the
knower and the known. And as
Sarah will talk about later,
there are some really good
reasons why we need to be very
careful as researchers and
scientists about thinking we
know more than we do, and not
listening to the subjects very
search. And as I said before,
all of these methods go
together. So I'm working on
building a citizen science
project currently, which has
been co created with members of
the autistic community to
investigate sensory processing
and autism. The participatory
research aspect brings autistic
people in at every stage of the
research process from so it
started with the James Lind
Alliance setting, priority
setting exercise which consulted
more than 1000 autistic people
about what questions needed to
be answered by autism research,
citizen science allows it to be
scaled and reach more people. So
a citizen science platform means
that it's not as intensive in
terms of one to one researcher
time. And open source
development is a wonderful way
of creating the transparency
that you need for participatory
science to be meaningful, as
well, as has we've been
discussing before in this
session. It allows you to
collaborate with all of these
incredible experts around the
world who can give you their
experience too. So now, Dr.
Sarah Markham, who is a
researcher herself, as well as
having lived experience with
autism, he is going to talk
about why participatory science
is important in relation to
heuristics in autism research.
So if he is there, do we have
Sarah here? Sarah, Marco. You do
now I was mute. I was muted.
Okay, that sounds a mystery.
Alright.
It's quite ironic that the worst
heuristic is in the title when
research has shown that autistic
people themselves are less
susceptible to many of the
biases that more neurotypical
people are capable of. But but
that's the presentation in hand.
Yes, changing approaches to
autism research. It's gone from,
you know, viewing, you know,
the, the the autistic person.
While a little Professor model
of Hans Asperger, we've
progressed onto the autistic
spectrum, looking at a multi
dimensional approach to autism.
And now we're now we have the
autism constellation model,
which kind of looks like a
crossover between a woodwork
project and string theory. We
can look at those dimensions
being curled up and perhaps
sometimes unfurling and, and
then curling up again. But the
exciting thing about
participatory science is that
it's a form of action research,
where the people the subjects
themselves are, in a way,
actually doing the science and
setting the protocols and
changing the protocols. They're
doing the versioning themselves
as they progress through the
scientific journey. So we're
kind of experiencing a paradigm
shift by this participatory
science approach. Thanks A way
of challenging conventional
static means of conducting
science, it's making it a more
agile, adaptive, evolutionary
approach. And it kind of will
hopefully help, in that sense
disperse some of the rigid
stereotypes around autistic
people. That's me.
Fabulous. Thank you, Sara. Um,
so I'm going to talk in a little
bit more detail about this
specific program, then myself,
see Sarah notice have all been
working on with a number of
other people. So this is on
spaces, and it's currently being
prototyped. And basically, it's
a website where autistic people
can share experiences of their
daily lives. And knows
experiences will then be used to
understand more about sensory
processing differences. So
around 90%, depending on the
study of autistic people have
sensory processing differences.
And it's sometimes been used as
a criteria of diagnosing autism,
although that fluctuates.
There's lots of lab based
studies into this. But there's
very little around how this
actually affects autistic people
and impact on their lives. And
so the idea is to use this data
set to pull out some common
themes, but also get a sense of
the diversity, and the
individual, like the granularity
of those range of experiences,
and use those to make
environments more accessible to
autistic people. For example, by
changing public policy modifying
environments, one thing I did
want to call your attention to,
in particular about this
platform is that the uses of
fine grained consent model. So
every single user can choose who
they share their experience
with, and for what purpose,
whether it's for research, or
published on the platform, or
both. And it's a dynamic consent
model as well. So they will be
able to withdraw their data
when, whenever they want, and
put it back as many times as
they like. And also, there's a
moderation process that is being
developed along with this
platform with artistic citizen
science scientists. So instead
of these things being imposed on
autistic people, by researchers,
this is really coming from the
autistic population, because
they know the most about their
own experiences. Um, this looks
a very busy slide. But it's I
think, for me, this is a lot of
the whole range of possibilities
that participatory citizen
science can. So one of the
things that I did in the last
lls cohort, because I did
cohort, too. And I can see
Katharina is here, actually, as
well, he's also been working
with me on the project. So hope
you're enjoying your life, I
learned a lot from it. This is
the kind of mapping exercise
that I did, and trying to work
out what all of the skills and
resources that were needed for
the platform were. And it was
important that autistic people
were involved in every single
aspect, as well as every part of
the research stage. So you can
see that this kind of circle
here, the yellow, it's artistic
people have been involved in
literally every part of this,
from hypothesizing, designing
the experiment, processing,
data, drawing, conclusions, and
so on. And also, as well as
lived experience, of course,
artistic people are people,
they're individuals with their
own unique skill sets. So a huge
amount of how the project has
been designed, is around those
unique skill sets, you can see
here, there's a whole range of
people being matched to skills,
including platform development.
We're entirely open source, the
protocols actually are all
published in a repository. And
it's available for reuse. were
linked into the train way and
amongst other things. So you're
welcome to join. If you're
interested, anyone can come
along. You can see here that
actually, open source knows my
research can work with people
who are not familiar with
GitHub, but are interested in
the project. So these are two
examples of working with
community members who are
citizen scientists to design
aspects of the project. The
first one is guidance on looking
through data and understanding
what you might want to remove,
or what you might think about
when you're deciding whether you
want something to be published
or not. When I wrote it was
these really academic jargony
paragraphs. And this is a
collaborator called James Scott,
who just broke it down into
these really beautiful,
extremely simple point by point
steps. And on the other side,
you see something that I was
working on with Sue, who I'm
going to pass over to in a
moment. This is a color coded
version of tasks that people can
do on GitHub from easy to
difficult so the green is You
may not have that much
experience, the read is you have
to be pretty advanced. And those
are now the labeling system for
all the issues on GitHub right
now based on C's design, to make
it more accessible for autistic
people. And so now I'm going to
pass over to sue. And she will
talk about her experience for a
little bit. And then after that,
I'll pass it over to Otis. So
over tc,
Hi, I'm Sue UI. And I turned 67
on Monday, and I was an HR
admin, but non digital
engagement of any kind, and
scientists were scientists and
people were people, and never
the twain should meet. So I been
involved in the focus groups and
stuff, I can actually totally
relate to what Sarah was talking
about the constellations because
my birth chart comes across as a
splash chart. So I have a
smattering of all sorts of
different things, including
creativity as opposed to
wordsmith. I'm great at
community engagement,
proofreading, newsletters, that
sort of stuff. So I was involved
with the focus groups, and they
moved on to the point where we
were developing the digital
platform without spaces, and
found myself learning this
different language and possibly,
Georgian, everyone learning
about my accessibility language.
Well, I'm reiterating things
from my birth my autistic
community, and my work was my
local Borough Council, London
Borough of Hammersmith and
Fulham. So, you know, doing this
stuff the labels was was great,
but also having the meetups
every fortnight where we invite
anyone who's worked on it with
us so far, and then new people
to collaborate with us. We've
purpose is it once a fortnight
so I've expanded my Twitter
account exponentially, I'm using
my protein everything to try and
hook people in. So some of the
people that I'm working with in
the OT space meetups are either
the scientists working both at
university level and new people.
So we supportive of everybody's
ability to be inclusive, and
accessibility is really
important. Because we don't make
it accessible the data input,
then we've nothing to extract.
And I'm actually in a new music
position, I work in the end game
with my borough, doing a new
Civic campus and public realm.
So I'm putting into practice my
influence on ambient
environment. And when those
buildings and public realm, I'll
be able to feed in data from my
experience navigating these
environments to add to the
platform. And it's that
reiterative kind of approach of
adding and building layers that
will make our stuff I think,
profoundly groundbreaking. And
I'm really grateful to be a part
of it. And today, I actually in
a different event, I take part
in a human library, which I can
send resource to someone, I was
being read as a as an autistic
book by someone from purposes in
their PR wing in London, and
they do a lot of clinical trials
with autism. So when I mentioned
our work on ot spaces, all the
pens came out, everyone started
writing stuff down. So I'm
looking forward to maybe seeing
some of the purposes, language,
perhaps joining in in the
future. So thank you for the
opportunity to speak with you
this evening.
Wonderful, thank you so much. So
you see the thing absolutely
amazing. And so as artists who
has been part of the project
from the very start, so I'm
going to hand over to him now.
And just to let you all know,
everybody is welcome to join the
meetup sessions that he was
talking about fourth Thursday,
of every month from 1230 to 230.
GMT. So, yeah, it's an open
invite over to you.
Hello, good evening for the
year. Hello, my name is Otis
Smith. I'm part of the citizen
science project and one of the
many countries about this budget
I myself have been autistic
since the age of 15. One of the
main parts of the project was
the opportunity and potential to
try and create a space for
autistic people that works,
appeals and benefits to all as
well as coordinating, expanding
the project further implanting
new skills, tools and resources,
thinking of different ways and
strategies to make the platform
authentic, accessible, engaging,
and interactive as possible.
Being a part of the citizen
science project has given me a
complete whole new meaning
outlook and purpose to improve
and be better. What I enjoy
about being included in the
citizen science project is that
everyone has their own take, and
contribution no matter how big
or small. Each take comes with
its own challenges as well as
discoveries implement a new
slicer questions and advice was
used in several effective
techniques and expertise and
having the opportunity to meet
and work alongside others
discussing agendas to sharing
new and effective ideas. It's
been such a privilege to be part
of this project. It's changed at
time. challenge my thoughts and
perceptions, reassessing and re
evaluating different topics and
strategies has been eye opening
and fulfilling at the same time.
This isn't science, but it
displays such depth into
character and representation of
the aims and does not look at
things in an unrealistic
approach to great players find
we want to ensure that the work
we put in can have such a
positive impact and make a
different reward for me. It's
not that the work we have
countries can hopefully expand.
Now it's not just a few, but the
money. Thank you.
Fabulous, thank you. Thank you
also to all of these wonderful
people, especially Christy
Whittaker, who is the PI of the
project is basically our vision,
and nelda, who was my mentor and
The Last of Us All of the
artistic community collaborators
and open source contributors and
lots of people here as well have
actually helped. So Katharina
malvika. Yo was health,
basically Thank you, everyone.
And here are some different ways
of joining in the project. If
you're curious