Carlos Martinez: Okay, so, Amy, I think
you're quite close to Amsterdam
Science Park, right? Amy: Yes, I am.
Carlos Martinez: I think that if you go to,
so there's a cycle path that
goes from Amsterdam Science
Park,
and and then you can cycle along
the canal for a bit, and then
you go through Weesp, which is
quite nice. And then you can
cycle all the way to Bussum.
So we did this one last summer.
And it is actually quite nice
because Bussum is like,
completely surrounded, it has
like a moat around the whole
city. So very nice cycle
patterns quite short. I think
for you it will be maybe under
an hour, you should be there.
Okay, now I'm hoping that
everybody else is who is
thinking, who is this guy? What
is he talking about? Why is he
ignoring the rest of us? And
what is he what what's the point
of this talk? That was exactly
my point is I'm doing this in a
presentation. Usually you start
by saying, Hi, my name is Carlos
Martinez, I work for the ISA and
center. And I'm going to be
talking to you about README
files, does the part of the
presentation where you usually
introduce yourself and tell
people, this is what I'm going
to be telling you in the next
five to 10 minutes. So I
deliberately asked Amy to help me
to do completely the opposite to
show a bad example of how you
should not make a presentation.
Because it's the same thing that
you have with a readme file. So
I'm going to be telling you
about README files, how README
files are useful to communicate
about your project. So README
files are really like a welcome
the welcoming part of your
project, they're the
presentation card for your
project, where you would say,
Okay, this is my introduction
card, this is my project. This
is what my project is about.
This is what my project does.
And it should provide you all of
the initial information for your
project for whether you're going
to what this project is about,
what I don't know if it's a
software project, what type of
software it is, which
dependencies it uses on which
language is written, what's the
what problem it solves. So these
are all the things that you want
to have in your README file for
introducing your project. When
somebody finds your project on
GitHub, and they read your
README file, that's the first
thing that they see does the
first impression that they have
about your project. And that's
the basically, that's the moment
where people meet your project.
And that's either they like
project or they don't like your
project, either they will use
your software or they will not
use your software. But a README
is very important, because it's
that first moment that is that
introduction to your project
these days, your projects
landing page is your projects
presentation card. So that's why
the README are very important.
Usually README in GitHub, you
on software projects, you just
have a file, which is a plain
text file called README with all
capitals, or README. Mark, you
can use markdown on README, as
well. And that's the first page
that you will have on your
GitHub repository. So in your
README, what are the important
things that you should have in
your README? If you should say,
what was your project is doing?
For whom? And why? So this is
really giving the context to
your project? You should tell a
what makes your project special?
Why did you build this new
software library that does the
same that other libraries, what
sets your your specific software
or your specific tool, or your
specific project apart from
other projects that are already
out there? And how do how to get
started? So if this is a
software project, how would you
install this tool? Or how would
you use it? Or if it's a, I
don't know if it's a book, like
the Turing way, how how you
would get started contributing
to this project? Or how would
you get started using this
project? And usually, it's also
also always a good idea to point
to useful resources about your
project. So again, if it's a
software project, and it's
already distributed through
package manager, where can you
find the link to To the package
manager that manages your
software, or if this is the
the README for a project, and
you have a website, maybe you
also want to point to your
website. So where are all the
other resources that are useful
and relevant for your project?
Okay. So again, in terms of bad
examples, good examples. If this
was my software project, and
this is my README file, this is
a terrible README file. So it
has the name of my project, and
it tells you how, how do I run
my code and how to cite my
paper? But it doesn't tell you
what my software does. Why would
you use it? In which context?
would you use it? What problem
does it solve? How is it
written? Where is the
documentation, so there is
absolutely no information about
it? Maybe it's useful for me to
remember how to run my code. But
even for myself, in three weeks
time, I will forget what my
project was about. And I would
remember was the tool that I was
using for this No, I don't know,
I don't remember anymore. So I
think this is the best example I
could think of of a terrible
README file. Maybe the The only
thing that could be worse is to
not have a README file at all.
Now, a good example, this is the
README file from the Turing Way.
These tells you what is The Turing
Way, it tells you that it's a
lightly opinionated guide, and
it tells you that it's aimed for
researchers, and I think, yes,
it also tells you where can you
find the the guide and in a
readable format, or not in the
README file format. So you can
go to the-turing-way.netlify.app
So it's telling you what it
does, who is it aim for and point you to
useful resources. And one thing
that I love is that you even
points you to README file in
different languages. So that's a
really nice example of a REAME
file. So yeah, so that those are
the main things that I think you
should be thinking, thinking
about when you write your README
file. So reiterating what they
already said is the welcome
message to your website, you
should share all the important
information about your project,
what's your project, mission
vision, what you want to do with
this project. And it's also a
good place where you can link to
relevant information, for
example, licenses, code of
conduct, which as we just heard,
from how it's important to state
your license for software
projects, and other types of
projects. Another thing that I
think it's important to consider
is where your software is going
to where your README is going to
be used. So if you write your
README on GitHub, and maybe this
is a little bit, I'm switching
to a very software specific
example. But if you're so if you
write a software tool, and your
software is on GitHub, your
users will look at your README
on GitHub, but they will also be
able to see your README in other
places, because once you connect
your GitHub account with other
places your README gets like
harvested by Docker hub or by PyPy
and your README ends up in
other places as well. And maybe
also your if you generate the
website automatically from your
GitHub repo, your README ends up
there as well. So it's always
useful to think, how is your How
are your readers going to read
the README? So try to always
consider who's going to read
your README file and in which
context, they're going to read
it.
And so README files context.
Now, what are my top tips for
reading? I think this is an
exercise I believe that we want
to do later. But
basically, I think that my take
home message on README files is
that you should always try to be
clear, and try to always think
of your reader always think
who's going to read it. What
information do they need? What
will they learn? From the readme
file and a What do I want them
to learn by reading my README
file. So what is information
that they want to convey to them