Unknown: Okay, so roadmaps, I
think all of us have some
understanding of what it is so.
But let's forget about that for
a second. And let's, let's
rethink what we know, in the
next sort of 10 minutes or so.
So what we'll be doing, at the
end of this call, I believe,
we'll be asking you to create or
revise a roadmap for your
project. That's only for project
needs. That's not fundamentals
or other friends. But yeah, so
in the next 10 minutes, let's
discover how to use a roadmap to
plan our work and contribution
on open projects. And we'll also
look at some examples. So you're
mentioned that open leaders
design and build projects that
empower others to collaborate
within inclusive communities.
roadmapping is not only about
designing, but more importantly,
we'd like to focus on empowering
others to collaborate. So again,
going back to that open
leadership framework, which I
really suggest you have a look
at after this call on in your
own time as well. This
roadmapping is really a tool
that we should use in our design
processes to to build a project
that really facilitates
participation, and inclusion. So
this is really, you'll see that
coming through later, as well as
I break down the roadmap. This
is really about governance,
about how we make decisions
about how we want to welcome
people into our communities and
about project identity. So what
the project is.
So
we want, the first step to allow
people to empower people to
collaborate with us in building
our projects is really to create
welcoming spaces. So I think
that we all want our projects to
be welcoming spaces. And to do
that, there's a couple of like
tips here you can see, so make a
good first impression. So that
your contributors and yourself,
you know that you're in the
right place, explain how
contributors can get involved in
your project. And then also, if
you think about it, it's really
helpful for people to know
what's happening at this point,
and what's coming next. So,
these are, these are kind of the
motivations to include these
three different components
within the roadmap. So we're
going to go through them one by
one in the next slides. But
first, this project summary and
welcome then how to get
involved. And then the timeline.
project summary, and welcome.
It's really important because a
lot of people get directed to
your roadmap, without you know,
any contracts or any prior
understandings, you really have
to assume that they maybe know
nothing about your project
beforehand. So I think it's
important that we welcome and
help orient our visitors so that
they understand where they are,
is often nice to have a project
summary, for example, to say,
you know, two, three sentences
of what your project is about.
And this also helps give a very
clear focus for ourselves when
you're writing the rest of the
roadmap. Oh, just one thing
before I moved on, yeah, you
might want to make that quite
welcoming in your own style, as
well. So so you know, you can
put emojis, for example, that I
like, but you have. The next
part is how to get involved. So
new contributors may be very
enthusiastic, and they may want
to jump right in. But it doesn't
mean that they know how to. So
it's really important that we
point to parts of the project
that they can immediately work
on. And then also point to
documentation and pages that can
help them check out you know,
what's, what's happening and how
they can contribute. And then
finally, we get to the timeline.
So that's really, yeah, the star
of a roadmap. So the timeline is
there to help us organize as
project leaders to organize our
tasks to complete our projects
around the milestones that we
will learn to set. And then also
to map what we're working on now
and what's going to happen next.
And you can imagine that if that
helps you organize things, and
it also helps you contribute or
understands how your projects
work timewise. So, milestones,
they are significant turning
points or events that will help
move the project forwards. So
typically, these are there could
be many types of milestones, but
typically they are like status
goals. So for example, an MVP so
a minimal viable That's like a
first release of your projects
or software or open book,
whatever you're working on.
These could be dates and events.
So it may be you are taking your
project to an open hackathon,
you may want to put that down,
because a lot of work will be
done during around that date in
that event. They could also be
timeframes. So that could be,
you know, short term goals
medium term. So maybe depends on
what you're trying to achieve,
but maybe what's going to happen
two or three months down the
line, and then what's going to
what you hope to see in the
year, let's say, so, you can
think about this for your own
projects, discuss this with your
mentor, and pick 123 milestones
for your timeline. And then once
you have those milestones, it
then makes it easier to break
things down even more. So to
achieve each of those
milestones, it's good to think
about what tasks needs to be
completed. So you can line these
up chronologically, or just
think about the stuff that needs
to happen, when those master
facilitate those milestones
happening. include information
with each of the tasks, so to
make it easier for contributors.
So for example, what needs to be
done pointers as to how you can
get started, or the reason why
those tasks exists. And those
should reinforce your vision.
So that was a very fast overview
of the components of a roadmap,
how do we make this open, and
that's very much determined by
also how you start the roadmap.
So you can store it in a
separate file. So if your folks
are familiar already with like
GitHub and or gitlab, or one of
these open project platforms,
then you may be familiar with
like markdown format. So you can
have a file called roadmap doc
and MD, and you will, you can
put your roadmap there, you can
put it in a readme file, again,
that's the introduction page
that you get in these open
repositories. You can put it in
an issue. Again, that's that's
referring to GitHub
infrastructure. I'll show you an
example in a bit and, or in the
Projects tab in GitHub, so many,
many ways that the idea is that
you drop this and you try to
make this openly available to
everyone who wants to look at
it. And also allow them to maybe
give you feedback or, or
comments on your work as well.
So let's look at one example.
This was very nicely done,
Barbara nice, I think when all
this one happened. That's a
roadmap for collecting
applications for less. So you
can see at the top is what is
all asked, Why are you like, if
you have no idea what all of
this is, at least the first
sentence will let you know that
open lifesciences and mentoring
and training program, and then
how to get involved. And then a
very detailed timeline with a
major milestone. So before open
applications, when applications
open when applications are
closed, and then the task in
between. So this is done in a
GitHub issue, as we can see
here. And yeah, that's what can
look like in real life. So there
are other examples on the slides
as well if you access the slides
later, and you can click into
them and check them out in more
detail. That's that. So yeah, we
hope that you know, this is an
introduction to empowering you
as a project leader, you already
have a lot of skills to be a
leader, but maybe we can help
each other do is to become more
open and open leaders and open
science ambassadors. So think
about what you'd like to achieve
and break that down and turn
that into a roadmap.