Unknown: When I talk about
unconscious bias, my question
here is does it really matter?
And my first slide, that doesn't
work. My first slide is about
this idea that this may
challenge you. And uncomfortable
truths is a buzzword that pops
up from time to time. And on the
right here, you've got really
bridges or six, in 1960, when
she went to a previously white
school, there was a black baby
doll in a coffin. And she was,
you know, they threatened to
poison her, she's six years old.
And she was only allowed to
bring food that she brought from
home for her safety. And,
and this is the challenging
thing. Because this is not this
person is still around, she
gives talks from what I can
remember. And you know, this is
a really, this is change is not
something that just happens very
lightly with very minimal
effort. And people just go, Oh,
you know what, it's okay. This
is this is the this is what
happens when you have to when
you bring about a change. So I
want to ask people to think
about not writing anything down,
but to think about the bias that
she received was a conscious or
unconscious bias. And I want
people to think about that for a
few seconds. And then I'm going
to give my take. So you get a
six year old, people are
threatening to kill up. Do you
think that's conscious or
unconscious bias?
So my take on this is, do you
think it mattered to Ruby? Do
you think that if someone
threatened you when you were six
years old, whether it was
conscious or unconscious?
Do you think it would matter?
And that's the sort of question
that I want to ask across a few
different other examples as
well. So Tamir Rice was 12 years
old when he was killed by a
policeman holding a replica gun.
He didn't make any verbal
threats or pulling his gun
towards the officers. He was
shot and killed very, very
quickly, by the time to police
it pulled up. It was a very
short amount of time before he
was killed. Do you think it
mattered to me if he was killed?
Because he was? Because the
police were consciously or
unconsciously bias? Do you think
it mattered to his family? In
2015, just doing a search on
racism in Belgium, I just picked
a country. There's a situation
where this person was lost the
leg after being chased by a
police car. And on Facebook. He
had statements about the kind
there and there's more, there's
more where that came from? Did
it matter? Did his left leg
feel? Did he lose his left leg?
And was it worse because it was
conscious or unconscious bias?
You know, when you start to
think about that, and all of a
sudden, this idea of conscious
bias doesn't matter.
Doesn't seem as important
anymore. To me. As a personal
opinion, you might have a
different opinion on that.
But I've shown you some really
obvious things. But what it does
is it's more subtle. So this is
really this happened just
recently with Vanessa karte got
cropped out from from a photo.
And it was just bizarre when I
first saw it, I just just
bizarre, I can't, I can't
explain it. But it can be more
subtle. And, again, whether
you're when you're the recipient
of this subtle bias, it can hurt
just as badly. Whether it's
conscious or unconscious, it
doesn't really when you're the
victim, and it doesn't really
matter. From what I could tell.
Bias also includes people who do
similar things getting treated
differently. So who gets
forgiven and who gets punished?
So one of the things that I like
to teach people is to actually
start to break down and say,
Well, can you think of another
example where someone's been
given a very different situation
where you know they're forgiven
or who punished so this is Brock
Turner, who's on the left is
very famously, was treated quite
nicely because I think the judge
recognized that he could have
been an Olympic swimmer one day
and they thought that it might
ruin his career if he was, you
know, treated like a person, or
treated like a, you know, as
someone who has to bear the
consequences of his actions. And
then you've got Diane Davis here
who gets five years in prison
for fish for a shoe for shoe
robbery.
And I think you just really
shows this idea I call it side
by side, when you actually start
to put these examples side by
side becomes really easy to see
who gets forgiven. And he gets
punished. This is actually
fairly close to home, say in
Australia, in Victoria and
Melbourne, where I live, there
was a lot of COVID happening in
the rich and affluent areas, and
people were just breaking things
and this guy was walking around
and you know, no people were in
Mars cafes were full. But in the
place where there wasn't that
much COVID there were cops that
are surrounding towers, in
effect, and they found out later
on that the the Ombudsman for I
think it was a human rights
ombudsman actually was saying
that, that lockdown, having
those police around the towers
was actually a breach of human
rights. And, again, the housing
Minister for Victoria just said,
we're not going to apologize for
that. And again, it's like who
gets forgiven and who gets
punished. And once you start to,
to understand that, and you can
do what I would call a simple
discourse analysis about who
gets forgiven or who gets
punished, it becomes really,
really obvious where those
biases lie. And these biases are
obstacles for people from
marginalized groups. And I
really love this picture,
because it actually says, Well,
actually, I'm just going to
judge you on who gets the finish
line. And they don't actually
judge the degree of difficulty.
And I'd also like to point out,
though, when I talk about
intersectionality, I'm talking
about having more belonging to
more than one marginalized
group. And so I like to think,
well, I don't like to think that
but I think of it as a power
function. So if you're from a,
you know, it's exponential, it's
exponentially more difficult to
be a person from two
marginalized groups and to be a
person from one marginalized
group. And incidentally,
actually, I'll leave that one
for a little bit later. That
story. So for me, when you talk
about unconscious bias, I'm
thinking we'll actually I think
we should send to the people who
are marginalized. So when you're
talking about unconscious bias,
you're centering the perpetrator
centering yourself, and I don't
think that's actually really
helpful. And this one that was
saying is like, you know, this
is just an easy get out, call it
cause for behavior that's bad,
and I don't really want to be
able to sort of focus on that.
So I think what we should be
doing is listening to the people
who are the most marginalized in
our society, because they are
the canaries in the coal mine.
And how comfortable they are,
how well treated they are, is an
indication for how healthy that
society is. So in Australia at
the moment, we are not a healthy
society. We are not a healthy
society. And it's been like that
for a while now. Because when
you look at the most
marginalized people in our
society, they're treated really
badly. And the way I like to
think of how we adjust this is
think of a triage in our
hospitals emergency department
has a lot of way to you don't
really need to think about it.
But the more marginalized a
person, the more we should help
them. Because the people who
aren't marginalized or
marginalized very much might not
need as much help. So when you
think about intersectionality,
and you're saying, Well, if
you've got more than one
marginalized pediment, one
marginalized group, it's almost
like having a heart attack you
want to be seeing, seen and you
want to be given as much help as
possible. If you just sort of
hurt your finger a little bit,
you shouldn't be the one at the
front of the queue. And then the
following two slides, I've got a
couple of graphs where I talk
about who we're actually
listening to, based on their
degree of difficulty. So this is
what I call the
intersectionality spectrum. And
this degree of difficulty is
something that I've sort of
calculated. So I'm a big fan of
George P boxes, quite all models
are wrong, but some are useful.
And the reason I show you this
is because I know it's wrong,
but hopefully it'll be useful.
And what we do in Australia is
we listen to people over on this
side of the one so white males,
white females, they they're over
represented in a lot of media.
in leadership positions, etc,
etc. We don't listen to people
over on this side.
Because actually, overall, like
I said, we're we're we are a
sixth type realistic society,
we're not a healthy society. And
if you think about it from a
triage point of view, and this
degree of difficulty is actually
calculated in a certain way, you
can sort of see it in the
spreadsheet. But well, the way I
see that we should do it, if we
were to do it in a triage point
of view, where this big arrow
here is like where we listened
to the most, that should be
actually on the other side, we
should be centering the people
over on this side. And just a
highlight here as well. I'm
sitting here. So I'm actually
extremely privileged. When you
look at when I looked at people
to my right, my, my family, my
immediate family is all to the
right of me. I'm the most
privileged person in my family.
And the way I think of things
is, how do I help people to the
right of me, because I don't
necessarily need to help people
to the left, as much as I need
to help people to the right, and
advice center, center these
choices. But it's not just
important to listen, we have to
show courage and act. So I
don't, there's a couple of
things in here that I just want
to show is what matters to
people. One on One lifelike
speech is how you're supported.
I think we mentioned a little
bit more about that inclusion,
it's like you know, you feel
supported. But you have to
recognize that if you're if
you're neutral, you're on the
side of the oppressor. Right. If
you're neutral, the system is
not going to change, it's going
to say, it's going to keep its
momentum. But to act to be to
fight the system, it actually
takes courage and a willingness
to sacrifice your privilege to
help others. So really
interesting, the only person who
agreed to teach Ruby, the six
year old was a white woman
called Barbara him, Henry. Now,
could you imagine what Barbara
would have had to go through to
actually do that for a whole
year, she was the only one who
taught taught Ruby, you can
imagine going into the into the
staff room there. And I don't
think you should have felt very
included. And then, but the
thing is, it's an act of courage
to be able to actually find the
system. And that's, that's not
easy. There are many times where
I have decided that I am not
going to fight. Because I do not
have any. I just don't have it
in me. So I was trying to find a
quiet, I couldn't find one. So I
stuck my brain in pologize. for
that. I'm right, you can read
it. For me, inclusion is being
comfortable. We all say these
things without losing my job
losing friends or damaging my
career. And I won't talk about
this with my friends.
Right. So here's some I always
like to end on, I think this is
near the end is on practical
things that you can do. You can
change your social media census
into sexually marginalized
people. In Ghana, if you were to
encourage people from
marginalized groups, and
identify talented people from
marginalized groups who may not
have had the opportunity. And
then these are ways that you can
use your privilege to step aside
to be able to allow people to
have the opportunities that they
missed. And if you're up for
looking at charities to change
the systems in your
organization's and is a really
great example. And it's
surprising how many times I've
seen this in the music industry,
where you have someone who's got
a lot of privilege, who's
saying, hey, if you give this
person a chance, I will make it
worth your while. And that
person became, you know, be able
to you know, I'd never had to
play a small jazz club again for
Ella Fitzgerald Fitzgerald. And
that was a sign of someone
sacrificing their privilege or
using their privilege to provide
an opportunity for someone else.
There was another situation I
think Fred Astaire did at
Princeton. Well, the artist not
only known as Prince did it as
well, but really interesting to
be able to see those things
happening. So in summary, for
me, unconscious bias, yes, no,
not really interested. For me,
it's about centering
marginalized voices, and trying
to support people from
marginalized groups to your
right in the intersectionality
spectrum. Everything else is
sort of not going to be as
helpful for the people who are
who are marginalized. If you
want to know more, I recently
tried to put together a workshop
a theoretical one called
improving the diversity,
inclusion and simulation, which
is got some of these things in
there. And there's some other
interesting things that are out
there. In terms of censoring
social media, if you're on
Twitter, I put down this list of
public it should be a public
place of people to follow. And
these are the people that are
sort of high frequency tweeters
probably going to take you out
of your comfort zone if it's not
already, who I use as my gauge,
and have really sort of followed
when I've started followings.
When I've started following
marginalized voices, I learned
way more than I've learned
anywhere else. But there's a
price to be paid. When I was
talking about this to someone
the other day, she said, Yeah,
I've noticed that I've learned a
lot more, but I'm way more sad
than I was before. Because a lot
of these stories of marginalized
people are either not they're
not happy stories. But you have
to go through that process to be
able to come out the other end
and say, Well, actually, it
gives me motivation to keep
doing these sorts of things to
bring about change. So I think
that is it. So I don't know what
happens now.