Unknown: I'm an elephant
involved. I'm a South African,
the living in South Africa all
my life, many generations now, I
live in a small coastal village,
there's a photo of what you can
see when you climb the hill just
behind my house.
And I work with universities
across South Africa, in Africa
and an outside of Africa, to
help researchers adopt
technology in their research.
What I'm going to talk to you
about today, as we said, was
personas and pathways, which are
two design elements that have
different benefits in your
project. It doesn't only help
you to think about designing the
right project, but it also helps
you to communicate within the
project and to your stakeholders
about design decisions that
you've made. And of course, it
helps you to attract the right
users, and contributors and help
them to stay in your project. So
for many of you are doing very
different projects, before this
talk, I was accurately looked at
the list of projects. Again,
it's so diverse. And some of you
might be thinking, well,
personas and polyphase aren't
really relevant to my project.
But regardless of what kind of
project you're doing in open
science, personas and pathways
can really help you a lot. So I
hope by the end of this project,
you'll see at the end of this
talk, you'll see a few ways in
which you can use it. So you
will need personas and pathways
if you want users and all
contributors. And for all the
projects that is in the URL
ESCO. Definitely, this is what
we want, right. Just very
quickly, what are personas. And
very recently, I was going
through the process of creating
personas for a project. And I
was looking at various personas
online various resources. And I
was stunned to see how many
personas seem to be created to
tick boxes to, to really, really
just not necessarily speaking to
the people that might be coming
to their projects. According to
Mozilla beside as an imaginary
user based on real world
observations and understandings
of actual potential current
users, and in our case, also
contributors. But what's really
important is that you have to
know your audience, you have to
know the people that you're
working with, to be able to
create an accurate persona. And
that's where the data comes in.
I think most of us in the school
definitely in the life projects
are aware of the importance of
data to inform decisions. And so
maybe at the beginning of your
project, you may not really know
your users or your contributors.
And we'll, we'll speak a little
bit more about that later. So
your your personas might not be
that accurate. But as you go
along, you can improve those
personas as you get to know your
users better. And as your
project grows in terms of
diversity and voices. pathways
are ways for people to stay
involved in your project. So you
may you may have people coming
in as developers, you may have
people coming in as users, and
what are the what are the things
that will make them come into
your project and stay involved.
So not every project that can
lead not every person that comes
into your project will
necessarily take on a leadership
role in the future? But how can
you help people to see how they
can be involved regardless of
what they what they resource or
skill level, or motivations are.
And we'll talk a little bit more
about that later on. For me, a
pathway is less about the
picture on the left, where there
is this golden highway that
takes you to where the sun
shines behind the mountain. And
it's more about something like a
treasure map where someone might
look at the map and say, Oh, I
want to go you know, have a look
at the river. And then someone
else might say I'm really fond
of forests. And someone else
might say well, I'm going to
take the little boat that's out
there and go across the ocean to
the other side of the peninsula.
So there are many different ways
that people can can be involved
and there's no expectation of a
leadership progression. Why are
scientists and pathways
important and the way that I see
it is personas will bring the
right people to your project and
pathways will help them to stay
there. Just getting back to when
he developed them, it's optimal
to develop them at the beginning
of your project, it might save
you a lot of time if you are
thinking about who you are
developing this project for from
the beginning, and also what you
want them to do there. And
thinking about your project in
terms of how it will grow, you
will need as the project go
grow, and what you can offer
your users and your
contributors. So typically, you
can develop personas and
pathways beginning. And then of
course, as I mentioned before,
use the data that you gather as
the project grows, as new voices
join your project to improve
those. The next slide is just an
image of the design thinking
process. And I really like this
one, I think there's a lot of
questions here that might be
useful to your projects beyond
just thinking about pathways and
personas. And and what I want to
show you is that projects, I
sometimes get the feeling that
in open science, every project
will just work like it has to
work, right because we invest so
much time and effort and emotion
into it. But the realities, and
sometimes projects, when you
can't get past the prototype
stage, you have to sit back and
really think about whether this
is the thing that was going to
be you know, do solve the
problem that you set out to
solve. And just going back to
the drawing board and looking
again, at your users looking
again, at your, at your
contributors, who did you think
you were going to attract? Who
are you really attracting, and
how you can edit that? I really,
I really like this one, I think
I'm going to be using this just
in thinking about our own
projects as well. The personas
typically fit into After
gathering the data through your
exploration and emphasizing in
the stage where you are defining
what specific needs are that a
person has that is coming to
your project. One of the things
that we've used in one of our
projects that every map or
project to think about who our
users and contributors could be
our mind map showing all the
roles that they are in a
project. And the reason why I'm
showing you this mind map is
because as you Google for
information about developing
personas, you might come across
a lot of references, that speaks
about developing personas, from
a company's point of point of
view, to attract users and to
get the rights, the rights
elements into a platform or a
software or a project for the
users. So really mostly about
users. But in open science
projects, and very specifically
in open community communities
and software development, we
have not only have to think
about our customer, the person
that will be using our tool or
our platform, or will be joining
the community as a community
member. But we also have to
think about personas and
pathways for people who are
developing, I apologize for my
dog barking in the background.
We have to think about our
contributors, our community
developers and other roles, not
only the users. So this kind of
mind map has helped me a lot to
think about personas from a user
point of view, from the learners
point of view. And then also how
can we attract developers and
what what are we giving to them?
How are we motivating them to
join the project and what what
we vote
on are getting here and how they
are they can use being involved
in our project to grow their own
skills and equities as well.
Another tool that I've used in a
different project is the
escalator project.
Here we used existing monitoring
and evaluation evaluation tools
to figure out who our target
target audience may be, who are
we developing this project for?
I'm going to talk about the
project a little bit later on
just in the next slide. But
first we started with using a
fishbone diagram to define our
problem very carefully. So
asking a lot of why's Why do we
see this problem and the problem
that we were seeing when I was
in South Africa, we have said
several groups that are working
in digital humanities and
computational social sciences
but we don't have a community of
practice. We don't have a
community that takes give a
speech stage I will lecture his
knowledge in South Africa in
digital humanities,
computational social sciences.
So that was our problem. And
then we were saying, so what why
do we have like, what do we
keep? If we have a community or
not a community? What are the
benefits of having a community
of practice? And needless to
say, there are so many, many
benefits of having that
community of practice. So it
wasn't hard to decide whether we
should take this project. But
then thinking about using the
fishbone diagram, which I don't
have an image here, but you can
Google for that. And just to
think about, why are we seeing
this problem, and that really
helped us to identify groups of
people who could benefit from
from this project. And then
after developing the the
fishbone diagram, we use the
theory of change, which is also
a really, really good tool,
especially for people who are
developing community projects
where they where you want to see
a change in communities. It's a
really lovely tool to to
consider using in your project.
Because as you are going through
asking these questions, you
really also start to identify
groups of people, which can
inform your personas, because
you're asking questions in a
different way. So just quickly a
theory of change, you take your
project your problem, and figure
out what is the impact that you
would like to see which will
address that problem? And then
you work backwards towards what
are the long term outcomes that
will lead to this impact? to
have those long term outcomes?
What are the short term outcomes
that you should see? And then
what are the outputs that you
will need to see the short term
outcomes? And then what are the
activities that you have to do
to create the outputs that
relate to the short term
outcomes and so forth? And then
really, what do you need as
inputs to be able to do the
activities that will lead to
that efforts were backwards from
the big problem, and the impact
that you want to want to see.
And by doing that, it has helped
us a lot to define groups of
people. And very specific, I can
see the personas now, who we are
going to attract in this
project, and supporting this
project, and also who can help
us help us help contribute and
provide leadership in this
project. Another thing that I
want to point to you, for those
of you who are involved in
change projects in community
change projects is just at the
bottom of the slide, the time
that it takes to see certain
changes, just for us to be
realistic. I mean, the analytics
projects are only three months.
And some of some of us expect to
see changes that that really in
communities takes many years to
take place. So just to be
realistic, and a bit more softer
on on yourself when you are not
seeing the change that you would
like to see the theory for the
project called escalator and
it's and one of the one of the
flagstone activities of this
project is to develop a digital
champions initiative. And what
we realized, initially, we
thought we'll just run one
mentorship program very much
like oh, is they'll be or they
will be a mentorship program.
And we're going to open it up to
people doing research in digital
humanities in computational
sciences. And we're going to
teach them digital and
computational skills to do to
use in the research. But as we
work through the theory of
change, and through the through
the fishbone diagram, we
realized, but there are people
who who are not very comfortable
using technology, even in day to
day management of their their
work. expecting someone to learn
to code in Python when they
haven't really used something
like Google Docs or some of the
other tools like that your
resume or other tools. Which
means online learning is
probably
a challenge and working alone,
probably not part of many
communities. So we developed a
different type of mentorship
program. And it's also not
necessarily mentorship in the
way that you see here in LA is
to address very specific needs.
And in this slide, you can see
that we now have six tracks. And
we begin developing content for
those tracks and also partnering
with existing mentorship
programs, to see how we can
build on work that exists. And
here's just another speaking
about pathways again, and I'm
almost finished. And I found
this when I was thinking about
pathways and this whole idea of
them All pathways in not all
participants in our open project
goes to leadership. And I found
this this lovely app by
alltrails, which shows all kinds
of different hiking routes in
your area, and then how
difficult it is how long it is,
how much innovation the time it
will take to finish it. and
various other folders, I really
liked it, I thought it was quite
a good example of what I mean.
Just to give you some numbers in
a recent study, on open database
service in GitHub, they found
that for the major open source
database projects, more than
19,000 people had contributed to
the project's main repository at
least once, which means like,
once in the entire life of the
project, only about 30% of them
have 30% people had contributed
in the last year, which are
called active contributors. And
only about 20% have contributed
more than three commits to a
repo. And you can imagine for
for all of you working on your
projects, how many commits Have
you made your repo and how many
other people have committed, and
just realizing that when people
are coming to your project, they
may only do one, one change. And
that will be used, that will be
useful to your project. And you
should, you know, value them and
make everyone feel that their
contribution is valuable. And
even if they don't go on to
become very, I just want to show
you this image without which I
found from in the Microsoft,
what is called the Microsoft
inclusive design manual, which I
thought was really, really
lovely. And I do share a link
there on the slide. If you
designed for people who have the
biggest challenges to contribute
or to be part of your project,
you are just reaching so many
more people who, as you can see,
for example, if you design for
someone who, who is blind, and
you, you can all also support
people who may have a temporary
problem like a cataract, and
also someone who have a
situational problem like a
distracted driver. So it's
really, really, really
beneficial to your projects to
think about the most difficult
way, the biggest difficulty that
someone will have to contribute.
And if you follow that, you
really make it easy easier, even
for your most qualified
contributors or participants. So
in summary, as you'll see
online, there are many ways to
develop the centers and
pathways. And I do give a link
just in the next slide to
resources that's provided by URL
is as well that can make you
think about your personas and
pathways. There's a lot of
information that you can put in
there. And there's a lot of
personas that you can develop
for Be realistic. Remember that
open, open projects often have
limited resources, as long as I
bring for the moment, and that
you would like to be to do more
as the project grows, that
should be okay. And of course,
your inclusivity will grow as
your project diversity cries.
And those just the last quote
was basically one value if we
were all forced to pick one,
that designers should have
respect to users time, dignity,
ability and means. And this was
by a Facebook developer
frederico Franchione. So now,
what Malbec and them have asked
is that you think about how your
favorite open source projects
have probably use personas and
pathways to attract and retain
you in the project. And then
there's also
for this week, you'll have to
develop your personas and
pathways for your project. And
there's a link there and the
links are also in the document
and it does not slide over time.
Sorry. Yes, thank you for your
time.