Unknown: If you come to open
source Open Science space, there
are three documents that are
essential to add to any project,
when we heard earlier is about
license, choose the license, add
a readme. So you're choosing a
license so people know how to
use your material. You write
README, so people know what it
is about, and if it's useful for
me. And last one is contribution
guideline and code of conduct.
So people can find your project
and know how to use it, people
can find your project and know
what it is about. But the
ultimate aim of any open source
project is that allowing people
to build upon it, the innovation
doesn't happen if there was
nothing before us. This is where
the contribution guidelines is
very important. So people know
that you're allowing them to use
it. But in a weird way, what we
will do in my talk, I'll try to
keep it concise, but also in a
way that you understand the
importance of involving people.
So we will consider how to
create a positive culture for
contribution and collaboration
and open projects give you a
practical example of how a
contributing.md file looks like.
But it doesn't need to be called
contributing.md. If you're not
using GitHub, it could be just
contribution guideline. and
choosing a code of conduct. And
please keep an eye on choosing,
we are building on lots of open
source projects. So we don't
need to build everything from
scratch. There's a lot of
material references out there.
Pick one that matches most your
values. So yeah, just so you
know, someone asked me if the
Cat Cat picture is used, I think
it has become our mascot. And
that's why if you go to our
Slack channel in random, we're
just literally randomly talking
about cats. So I'm malvika
Sharon, I am the community
manager of the during rate,
which is the daytime job besides
open life science. That's not my
Twitter, but I left it there
because a lot of ideas that I'm
going to talk about comes from
Lily Winfrey. And I definitely
totally recommend you to follow
her little scientist, you can
follow me as well. But I'm
always talking on slack. So I
don't think you need more noise
from me. So what is a project
culture? When we want to build a
project culture, we need to
think about if we want to build
a community, is this a project
that I'm creating just for
myself? Or do I want people to
come in and hang out with me? If
I want people to hang out with
me? How do I want this community
to look like? How would we How
would my members be? Are they
going to bring the same idea as
me? Or are they going to be
diverse that they bring
different perspective, they
challenged me in building my
project, so I can achieve better
than I can do alone. These
people are also who help you
build and guide the culture,
right. But as a project leader,
it's your responsibility to set
the tone for how your community
should look like. Therefore you
need to make conscious decision
when you're writing a readme
page, or when you're selecting
the license. And when you're
creating contribution pathway
for others. When you're creating
these culture, you need to
understand what your personal
values that you're bringing in
project are hence it becomes a
project value. And how should
people behave? Setting
expectation is very important.
When someone enters a new space,
one of the biggest fear they
encounter is not knowing
anything, they don't know what
to expect. They don't know how
to behave, they don't know what
kind of behaviors are accepted.
Therefore, it's important for
you to let them know that this
is what this project stands for.
And this is how you can
contribute. And there are a lot
of unwritten rule which you want
to get out of your brain and
write it in a document that
someone else can actually read
it because no one can read your
brain yet. A project culture
involves more than just setting
a GitHub repository or telling
people by email that hey, come
and join me there is a lot more
to collaboration than that. It's
more than just a common goal or
having different teams working
on different parts, or
exchanging knowledge but also
understand what actually creates
those kind of values. For
example, if you have to be
intentional about the fact if
you want a diverse team, and
therefore make an attempt to
create a diverse team yourself,
things won't happen naturally,
you need to invest into it. If
you want to create an inclusive
workspace, you need to add a
code of conduct you need to make
sure that people are treating
each other kindly, therefore,
they want to be around each
other. And also when you open a
conversation for discussion, say
that this is open for discussion
and say that you're inviting
them to be part of it. So it's a
language, it's set of norm,
people's expectation, the tools
that you use and how decisions
are being made. It's a project
identity.
So how to build your culture
documents Clear contribution
guideline and the code of
conduct that is enforced. Going
back to what is community
community, in an ideal world is
a set of different people who
come together and live in an
ecosystem that is nurturing for
them. They don't have to be same
opinion, they don't have to be
same background, they don't have
to be same expertise, people
need, people should be allowed
to bring them their skills, and
combine them in a way that their
outcome is a lot more powerful
than the sum of their parts. And
then what is contribution?
Right? If we just talk about
GitHub in GitHub, again, next
week, we'll explore a lot more
about GitHub. So if you're new
to it, I will try to make sure
that I don't use jargons. But in
GitHub, you can go and write
issues that a lot of you have
created in oil s3, you've
created an issue and you've
become actually a contributor of
that repository. And this is a
picture from the touring way,
you can see Sarah here, and
that's me. And there are lots of
other folks. In the GitHub, you
put it as a file, which is
called contributing.md. And as I
said, if you're not working on
GitHub, you would still create a
page that that would be called
contributing or contribution
guideline. Why is it important?
So you want to define what the
structure of contributions look
like, provide guideline how to
make those contribution, you
ensure that there is a
consistency across your
community, if people are working
in different time zones, if they
are not talking to each other,
at least they have one place
where they know how to find
information. And when you write
all these down, it actually
improves the efficiency, you
don't need to always repeat
yourself and tell everyone over
and over what what all these
guidelines stand for. And it
also allows you to involve new
people, even if you don't know
who they are, at the moment, if
they are able to find your
repository, they have this
guideline to guide them how to
contribute to your project. And
who's responsible for that,
first of all owners, meaning
people who are leading the
project, they are responsible to
create it. contributors, which
are all members, they are
responsible to follow it. And
consumers like users and
members, they can also decide if
they want to share feedback with
you. So this is a very, very
good contribution guideline from
the carpentries. The carpentries
is another open source community
that teaches people how to teach
computation. And it is a it is a
wonderful page, because it's
it's just a community page that
gives you links to all the
places you can find information.
So if you're lost, you want to
come back to this page. And you
know, okay, I wanted to look at
trainers or I wanted to look at
champions. So you if you have
this one page, which is called
page of all links, that would be
extremely useful for people to
come back and orient yourself.
But these are generally
optional, because when the
projects are quite new, you
don't really have a lot of files
that you want to you want people
to read. You want to create a
place for diverse community,
right? And you would expect that
everything is going fine, and
everyone's super happy. But what
happens if something goes goes
wrong? What if things are not
ideal anymore, you want to make
sure that people have a place to
feel welcome and protected.
Therefore you want to give them
a code of conduct. Code of
Conduct is a set of rules,
sorry, a set of rules that
outlines the social norms roles
and responsibilities of an
individual project, party or
organization. It's commonly
abbreviated as C OC. So
generally, I would probably just
randomly say C OC, but that
really stands for code of
conduct. Do you really need to
see your C? Yes, you do need to
see it invites people to your
project. It sets clear
expectation in your community
and tells contributor that you
care about your community. Often
the misconception is that CLC is
a policy that is making people
scared about the fact that they
will be there will be
consequences. But honestly, CLC
is setting tone for your
community and making sure that
people who would generally not
become part of another community
because they don't really know
if you're welcome. It allows
them to look at what are the
guidelines, if someone harasses
them? Would there be any
consequences or not. And they
can make a choice based on your
community culture if they want
to become part of it.
There are some examples and I'm
going to just quickly show you
CSV con, which is one of the
newest code of conduct that they
had developed last year. It's a
conference. So they start with
what this code of conduct is,
who does it apply on. And they
also have two things which is
called enforcement and
reporting. And I'll quickly go
through that part as well. So
here it is, right. They have
code of conduct. Code of Conduct
is Not just a box ticking item,
right? So it's not like oh, I
want to add all the documents
that I would need to add. And
therefore I need to add code of
conduct without really reading
it or meaning it. It's not
enough. You need to add
enforcement and reporting
guideline, you need to make sure
that people know how to report
who the report is going to and
what will be the process for
reports to be followed through.
And often you would want to have
anonymous reporting, because you
don't want to put pressure a lot
on people. So getting started, I
would say that start by
brainstorming core words that
represent your community value,
consider behavior that you want
to encourage, think of the
process for incidents and
complaints and what are the
consequences for those acting
outside the norm, and understand
and accept your role as project
lead. So before we go, at the
end, you need to understand that
open source has a lot of work
that is always thankless people
are doing a lot of work at the
background. Therefore, you need
to encourage and reward good
practices, you can if you are
willing to and if you have the
capacity to designate a code of
conduct and safety committee to
Sir, make sure that your code of
conduct is quite visible and
clear and communicate the
process to contributors.
Generally, as I said, Don't try
to create your own code of
conduct. There are a lot of
great examples of code of
conduct that you can take and
adopt for your community.