Unknown: So, official Welcome to
open Life Science from my side
as well, very excited to have
you all on the call, I'll give
you a very quick overview of
what this program is about and
what you will be learning. So
you met Bernie's, and you and
me, we are the organizers of
this program. And we will always
have me in the call who will be
co hosting this with us. So as a
team, we believe that to be
effective, science should be
shared openly with others and
made freely available. And
you're here with us to do
similar amount of work that we
have planned for you. And we
have also done in our program.
We're here to share what we have
learned and we hope that you
will find them useful. The open
Life Science program has been
designed to help early stage
researcher and potential
academic leaders to become open
sense ambassadors, maybe this is
a bit outdated, because we've
seen a lot more different
varieties of project coming to
the program. And a lot of you
are probably not academic or
early career researchers. So
please don't think that this is
very much limited to this
definition anymore. So again, we
think that science can advance
only we share our work with
other and not, NOT gate keep it
or compete for knowledge that
others can benefit from. But
often, researchers are very
skeptical about sharing their
work due to their fear of
getting scooped being criticized
or not knowing what they can or
cannot share. Because often, one
of the rewards that we have in
research is paper and a lot of
papers are tend to be novel. So
this novelty often reduces the
chances of people sharing work
from the beginning as they're
developing. In this program, we
will discuss how to work openly
without becoming scientific
vulnerable. What we would like
to do is to share information
around how you can own the work
that you've done, but at the
same time, be collaborative and
open your project for others to
come along and work with you.
And together, we will explore
the important concepts in open
science and apply them in our
work one step at a time. Our
cohort calls are organized every
second week, but you will have
one week breather period where
you will have a chance to apply
the topics that you'll learn
about, apply them in your work,
talk to your mentors, but also
have a chance to talk about
those in slack or on GitHub
issue tracker that we will share
towards the end of this call. So
this is something that is just a
reminder, because you all know
it's a 15 week long Mentorship
Program, which ends with one
week of graduation. With people
finishing and sharing about what
they have worked on you will be
attending cohort based training.
If you can't attend it, you will
be able to access all the notes
and videos on YouTube. And you
will be able to talk to us a
week later in an open office
hour to discuss any topic that
you didn't understand or some
clarification might be useful
for you. We will also give you
lots of assignments. And these
assignments are not to be
judged. So we want to look at
it, it's really up to you how
you take those assignments and
apply them into your work. So
it's a lot of reflective and
experiential learning for you.
If you are really, really
excited of what we are teaching
you there are a lot more
information out there. And one
of the things that open licenses
built upon is Mozilla open
leadership principle. And all
the materials are online under
CC by so if you feel that you
would like to learn a little bit
more, this is something that you
can always visit, we will also
add the link in the chat for
you. The idea of open leadership
is that everybody can become
open leader because open leaders
are people who design build and
empower their projects and
communities for understanding
sharing and participation and
inclusion. So, I would like to
show you this table and this
table is something you will see
quite a lot as we bring expert
speakers and they show you
different topics. So we go
through design, build empower,
and we build for the
understanding, sharing and
participation and inclusion. So
every time we are working and
developing certain aspects of
our project, we need to think
about am I designing it for
people to understand it? Am I
designing it that people can
share or build upon my work is
it actually participate true
inclusive. So this is a thought
process that we will go one by
one so you don't need to
remember it but this is a
principle that we hope you will
be able to integrate in
everything that you're doing
within open science.
Again, open science is a huge
umbrella term. It can have lots
of topic that you isn't just
restricted to open source
software or open access
publication. But there's a lot
more about open science that you
might be interested in. So as
you heard everybody have really
diverse ideas. Some of you might
want to share data openly, which
falls into the term open data,
you would like to share your
code, which is open source
software. Some of you have
hardware design, which is open
source hardware. Of course, you
know about papers and protocol,
which can be published in open
access. We also want to
encourage you to share your
results earlier, which is
preprint, sharing prep paper
reviews in open reviews. Many of
you are working on open
education and citizen science.
And we would like to bring you
all together so take the
opportunity to get to know each
other as well, because
scientific networking is also
part of open science. Open by
design is something we would
like you to remember because
open by default is not often
inclusive, or participatory or
community LED. But when we
design them into our project, we
can make sure that everything
that we are doing is actually
built for inclusion and
community. So one of the studies
in 2012, which had included
about 160, tech companies found
that the level of strategic
intent in openness and not just
openness alone correlates with
market performance. You can also
think about designing openness
into your work and it shouldn't
be a thoughtless default. This
is something that we want to be
extremely intentional about. And
I think that's what is in the
core of open Life Science
Program. You all are leaders,
and we believe that with your
leadership and your vision
combined with what we are
teaching in this program, you
can achieve a very positive
cultural change in your
community. And we hope you will
take the chance to exchange
those ideas and thoughts with
each other